<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Megista kai timia epangelmata, or, The vertue, vigour, and efficacy of the promises, display'd in their strength &amp; glory duly methodified and fitly applyed to every Christians particular case and condition, in a soliloquy, wholly scriptural, between the soul and the comforter : with a divine rapture of the soul, now resting satisfied by the spirit of the holy promise / by Tho. Henderson.</title>
            <author>Henderson, Tho. (Thomas)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1446</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18112492</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18112492</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106836</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43323)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106836)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1124:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Megista kai timia epangelmata, or, The vertue, vigour, and efficacy of the promises, display'd in their strength &amp; glory duly methodified and fitly applyed to every Christians particular case and condition, in a soliloquy, wholly scriptural, between the soul and the comforter : with a divine rapture of the soul, now resting satisfied by the spirit of the holy promise / by Tho. Henderson.</title>
                  <author>Henderson, Tho. (Thomas)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 130, [10] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Dor. Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First four words of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: [10] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, stained, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106836:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: OR THE <hi>Vertue, Vigour,</hi> and <hi>Efficacy</hi> OF THE PROMISES Diſplay'd in their <hi>Strength</hi> &amp; <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Duly methodiſed, and fitly applyed to every Chriſtians particular Caſe and Condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IN</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy,</hi> wholly Scriptural, Between the SOUL and the COMFORTER. VVITH A Divine Rapture of the SOUL, Now reſting ſatisfied by the Spirit of the HOLY PROMISE.</p>
            <p>BY THO. HENDERSON.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Fear thou not, for I am with thee: be not aiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayed, for I am thy God: I will ſtrengthen thee, yea, I will help thee, yea, I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteouſneſs,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 41. verſ. 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Dor. Newman,</hi> at the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons Arms in <hi>Little Britain,</hi> 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:106836:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106836:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <p>NO ſooner doth poore Man come out of the Womb, but he launcheth forth into an Ocean of Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Woes; where he is toſſed with Waves,
<pb facs="tcp:106836:3"/>diſtracted with Terrors, and encompaſſed with continual Evils, that follow him unſeparably, as the ſhadow follows the Body, and never leave him, till he get beyond the bounds of Time, and enter thoſe Interminable Manſions of Eternity; Neither is it any wonder for thoſe who are born Souldiers, to meet with Conflicts; for Travellers to meet
<pb facs="tcp:106836:3"/>with hard Uſage; for Sea-men to meet with Storms; for Strangers in a ſtrange Country, to meet with ſtrange En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment: For ſuch, indeed, are Chriſtians, men of another World, and here from home, travelling to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Kingdom, to that City of the Living God, the Coeleſtial <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to be aſſociated with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Angels, and
<pb facs="tcp:106836:4"/>the Aſſembly of the Firſt born; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould rejoyce that they are predeſtinated unto a Conformity to Chriſt their Head, as in Grace and Glory, ſo in Abaſement; and by that way of many Tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (which the Captain of their Salvation hath conſecrated) to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Yet he that is the Life and Light of the
<pb facs="tcp:106836:4"/>world, (who loved us better than his own life, which he layed down for us, and made it his laſt ſuit to his Father and our Father, that we might be with him) to ſhew us the way to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, hath given us his Word for a Lamp, his Spirit for a Guide, and his precious PROMISES wherewith he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpangled the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, to ſhine to us
<pb facs="tcp:106836:5"/>with their chearfull brightneſs, to lead us to theſe Azure Vaults, as being the only place of our repoſe.</p>
            <p>The Scriptures, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, are the power of God unto ſalvation, as full of Life, as the Sun is full of Light; and truly the Light is ſweet (ſayes <hi>Solomon</hi>) but as the Suns looſe disſhevelled Rayes (when he maketh the Horizon to laugh, and
<pb facs="tcp:106836:5"/>paints the Eaſt with Vermilion, ſpreading the Morning upon the Mountains) are not ſo glorious, as when the King of Planets himſelf comes forth out of his Chamber like a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom cloathed with Majeſty, and culminates to the height of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens in the Radiancy of his Splendour, poſſeſſing all his far extended Rayes, condenſed, and
<pb facs="tcp:106836:6"/>concentrated in himſelf, even ſo may the <hi>Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> as a gliſtering Light, thinly diſpenſed through the Scriptures, be leſs conſpicuous, poſſibly, and efficacious, than when they are aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, united, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalled, in ſuch Strength, Method, and Order, as to be rendered more Splendid, Illuſtrious, and Uſeful in all Exegencies; which I have weakly
<pb facs="tcp:106836:6"/>eſſayed to do in this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual, not without ſome hope, that it may prove a Sovereign Remedy againſt all deſpondency of Spirit throught unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, effectual by the grace of God to heal all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Maladies, and to compoſe all Diſtempers; for here you may behold with one view, as it were, the Stars of the firſt Magnitude, that are ſowen througout the
<pb facs="tcp:106836:7"/>Scriptures, and a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation of all the PROMISES, ſending forth their moſt pure, and active Influences upon the Priſoners in the Pit, labouring un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Spirit of Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and with Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Trepidation waiting for the coming of the PROMISE, and the Harveſt of Joy, after their Seed-time of Sorrow. Whatſoever
<pb facs="tcp:106836:7"/>be the Lot of a Chriſtian in the Valley of Tears, whether he paſs through the Land of the Living, in the fair Sun-ſhine of Proſperity; or in the black Shadows, and Night of Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity; yet ſhall he be ſtill aſſaulted by Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, either upon the Right Hand, or upon the Left, in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which Caſes this ENCHERIDION,
<pb facs="tcp:106836:8"/>like <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Staff may ſupport him, this ſhining Torch may ſerve him as a Cynoſure to direct his Courſe amongſt the Shelves, the Rocks, and the devouring Gulfs in the way, that he be not led unto the Chambers of Hell, and by depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Living God through unbelief, fall into the Pit of Perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In all or moſt of their VVritings, eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb facs="tcp:106836:8"/>the vanity of the Nations, it may be ſaid in ſome ſort, that <hi>Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam ſuperat opus,</hi> the form of the Piece, and the Art excels the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; but in this little Repertory of the <hi>Sacred Promiſes it is quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary;</hi> for here is nothing but Gold, and a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Rubies, Roſes of Diamonds, more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious then the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers Stone; and if they
<pb facs="tcp:106836:9"/>be not ſo fitly Set, and Enamelled in ſo good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Dreſs, as well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes them; Let this Little <hi>Eſſay</hi> (the firſt, I <hi>ſuppoſe, of any that has ever yet appeared of this kind) excite others, who are bleſſed and beautified with more of the Spirit of God, in VViſdom, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, and in Knowledge to deviſe cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Works, and to work in Gold &amp; Silver,</hi> Ex. 31.3, 4
<pb facs="tcp:106836:9"/>To improve their beſt endeavours and skill, to fet forth the Riches of Gods free Grace, in the fulneſs and ſweetneſs of the <hi>Promiſes,</hi> to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and comfort of the Heirs of Salvation. And yet I doubt not but who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever would receive the Truth, and not deſpiſe the Conſolations of the Almighty, ſhall find this little Sanctuary of the <hi>Promiſes, (even as they
<pb facs="tcp:106836:10"/>are here managed againſt all Objections, that may oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr) to be a Shield, which all the Fiery Darts of the Devil, cannot pierce; no Weapon that is formed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it ſhall proſper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here (in ſhort) thou mayeſt ſee muſtered, the Armies of that Roaring Lyon, diſplaying a Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner againſt the Heavens, who (as he was a Lyar from the beginning, and envying the felicity of
<pb facs="tcp:106836:10"/>man, adopted to that Eternal Glory, which he had forfeited) doth ſtill make it his work to ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize God to Man, and Man to God, and Man to Himſelf, thereby to diſturb the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and (if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) to diſappoint the holy purpoſe of God, towards the Veſſels of Mercy, and to render them Complices of his guiltineſs, and Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb facs="tcp:106836:11"/>of his everlaſting Torments. On the other hand thou ſhalt ſee the Impotent Forces of that Grand <hi>Impoſtor encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the Lyon of the Tribe of</hi> Judah <hi>(who is ſtronger than the ſtrongeſt, and prevaileth alwayes when he contendeth) and vanquiſhed by Him, who aboliſhed Death, and brought Life and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, to light through the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106836:11"/>
            <p>If there be any who through worldly Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, or other Indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, cannot travel through the more ſpaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Garden of the Holy Scriptures, to gather ſuch Medicaments as they would chooſe for refreſhing their Souls, they may without any trouble enter into this pleaſant Paradiſe, and delightful Grove, where they ſhall find rich Beds
<pb facs="tcp:106836:12"/>of all the Flowers, the choiceſt, the ſweeteſt that can be there afforded, all ſpringing from <hi>the Root of Jeſſe,</hi> and that Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Plant of Renown,</hi> which perfumes the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and the earth; Here they may have the great conſolations of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures diſtilled in an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixar,</hi> which by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of a Spiritual taſte, they ſhall find as the <hi>ſpiced Wine, and juice
<pb facs="tcp:106836:12"/>of Pomegranates,</hi> mighty to ſtrengthen the Heart when it faints, the Faith when it fails, and the Spirit when it is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed within them: A true <hi>Catholicon</hi> and <hi>Panacea</hi> for reviving the Soul in all <hi>Deliquies,</hi> and maintaining it in a good plight continually: A Poſie of more delightful and ſal;utiferous Flowers, than any that ever grew in the Garden of <hi>Eden:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:106836:13"/>A rare and rich Jewel of ineſtimable value, though of ſmall price, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as eaſie as neceſſary to be carried about by all thoſe who pretend to Chriſtianity and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO. HENDERSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106836:13"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A SOLILOQUY (Wholly Scriptural)</hi> Betwixt the afflicted <hi>SOUL</hi> and the <hi>COMFORTER;</hi> wherein all, or moſt of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections and Complaints diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed through the Scriptures, are anſwered and redreſs'd by other Conſolatory and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing Scriptures.</head>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>I Have ſinned, I have ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.13, &amp; 23.10, 17. <hi>Job</hi> 7.20. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.18, 21. The Great, the Mighty, <hi>Jer.</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:106836:14"/>32.18. the jealous God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5, 9. who by no means will clear the guilty, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Num.</hi> 14.18. What ſhall I do that I may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? <hi>Act.</hi> 16.30. Thou haſt ſet my iniquities in thy ſight, my ſecret ſins in the light of thy countenance, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 90.8. I am loſt for ever, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12, 17, 21, 23. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.11. O that thou wouldeſt pardon my tranſgreſſions, and take away my iniquities! <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.21.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>Who is a God like unto thy God? <hi>Mich.</hi> 17.18. Gracious and merciful, ſlow to anger, and of great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6. Chap. 30.9. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">I have ſinned againſt thee.</note> 9.17. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 86.15.111.4.103.8.112.4.116.5.145.8. &amp; 117.2. who pardoneth iniquity, and paſſeth by tranſgreſſion. He retaineth not his anger for ever, becauſe he delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in mercy; he will turn again,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106836:14"/>he will have compaſſion upon thee, and ſubdue thine iniquities; he will caſt all thy ſins in the depths of the Sea, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.18, 19. for as the heaven is high above the earth, ſo great is his mercy towards thee; As far as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, ſo far hath he removed thy tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions from thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.11, 12. he will cleanſe thee from all thine iniquities, and pardon all thy ſins, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.2. <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.8. &amp; 37.23. &amp; 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. Thou haſt Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with the Father, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.1. and the Father himſelf loves thee alſo, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.27. He will not deal with thee after thy ſins, nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy wicked ways, and corrupt doings; know that he is God the Lord, <note place="margin">Who by no means, &amp;c.</note> that works with thee for his own Names ſake, <hi>Ez.</hi> 20.9, 14. whereunto whoſoever flies, <hi>Prav.</hi> 18.10. And upon which, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever calls ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.21.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106836:15"/>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.13. It is his glory to paſs over a Tranſgreſſion, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.11. By Grace ſhalt thou be ſaved, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.5. And by hope. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24. Believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <note place="margin">VVhat ſhall I do? &amp;c.</note> and thou ſhalt be ſaved, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.31. For He, even He it is, that blotteth out thy tranſgreſſions, as a thick Cloud, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.25. &amp;c 44.22. He caſteth all thy ſins in the depths of the Sea, <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.19. He putteth away thine iniquities for his own ſake, and wil not remember thy ſins any more, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 103.11, 12. He beholdeth no iniquity in <hi>Jacob,</hi> and ſeeth no tranſgreſſion in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Thou haſt ſet my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 23.21. For in his Name (through whom God was recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling the world to himſelf, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. Thou haſt Remiſſion of ſins, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.43. Yea, thou haſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved abundance of Grace, and of the gift of Righteouſneſs unto Eternal Life, through Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.15, 16, 17. hope in the Lord;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106836:15"/>for with the Lord there is mercy, and with him there is plenteous Redemption, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.7. Behold the Lamb which taketh away the ſins of the World, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.29. who bare thine iniquities, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.11. whom God hath exalted with his right hand, to be a Prince and a Saviour, for to give repentance and forgiveneſs of ſins, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.31. to put away thy ſins by the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of himſelf, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26. The Blood of Chriſt Jeſus cleanſeth thee from all ſin 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7. Which he purged by himſelf, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. For he loved thee, and waſhed thee from they ſins by his own blood, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. And became the propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for thy ſins, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.2. which are forgiven thee for his name ſake, <note place="margin">O that thou wouldeſt pardon, &amp;c.</note> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.12. He will abundantly pardon, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 55.7. <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.8. Fear not, for it is thy Fathers pleaſure to give thee a Kingdom, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.32. Rejoyce, for thy name is written in Heaven,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106836:16"/>
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.20. And in the Lambs Book, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.27. O Bleſs the Lord that forgiveth all thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.3.8.: <hi>Col.</hi> 2.13. Which though they were, as Crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Scarlet, yet ſtall they be made as white as Wooll and Snow, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.18.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>Why haſt thou ſuffered me to err from thy ways, and hardned my heart from thy fear? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.17. Why wouldſt thou take thine holy Spirit from me? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.11. And wilt not deliver me from the power of Darkneſs, deluſions, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.10. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. O that I knew where to find thee, that I might come near to thy ſeat! <hi>Job</hi> 23.2. And remember thee of the Word of Truth which thou gaveſt me, wherein thou cauſedſt me to hope! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.49. And tell thee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106836:16"/>how thou didſt promiſe to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy Truth above all thy Name, <hi>Paſal.</hi> 138.2. But now my hope is as the giving up of the Choſt, <hi>Job</hi> 11.20. And I am cut off: for my part, <hi>Ez.</hi> 37.11. Is it good to thee that thou ſhouldſt oppreſs? <hi>Job</hi> 10.3. Wilt thou deſtroy the works of thine own hands? <hi>Job</hi> 10.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.8. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.1. and deſpiſe <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.6. the price of thy Sons blood? <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12. 1 Cor. 6.20. and 7.23. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>Who hath directed the Spirit of the Lord, or being his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour hath taught him? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.34.1 Cor. 2.16. <note place="margin">Why haſt thou ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered me to erre from, &amp;c.</note> Though darkneſs encompaſs his Throne, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.9, 11. and he gives no account of any of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>Job</hi> 33.12. Yet all the wayes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106836:17"/>of the Lord are mercy and truth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.10. He is only wiſe, I <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. There is no ſearching of his underſtanding, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.28. and his love paſſeth all knowledge, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.19. He has left thee to declare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee the thoughts of thy heart, <hi>Amos</hi> 4.13. And that he might humble thee, and prove thee, and do thee good in the later end, <hi>Dent.</hi> 8.16. But he will give thee a new heart, and write his fear up on it, that thou maiſt not be able to depart from him, <note place="margin">Take thine Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit from me, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.40. He will pour out his Spirit upon thee, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.17, 18. He will put a new Spirit within thee, <hi>Ez.</hi> 11.19. and 18.31. and 36.26, 27. Thou haſt received of the Spirit of God, 1 Cor. 2.12. even the Spirit of Adoption, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. and the Spirit of his Son, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. in whom are hid all the Treaſures of VViſdom, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.3. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106836:17"/>the Spirit of promiſe, whereby thou art ſealed, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. even the Spirit of Truth, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, who ſhall abide with three for ever, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.16, 17. That by the ſpirit of VViſdom that he has given thee, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.9. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8. Thou maiſt be able to comprehend what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and heighth of his love, <note place="margin">O that I knew where to find thee!</note> 
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.18. And know when to find him on the Throne of Grace, and cry <hi>Abba,</hi> Father, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. For he calls thee, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. and 25.34. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.37.1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. And will not hide himſelf from his own fleſh, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.7. Yea, he has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from the Heavens, and came out of the boſom, <hi>Fo.</hi> 1.28. of the Father, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.9, 10.1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.17. and 17.8. to ſeek thee, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.10. Ez. 34.11, 16. to finde thee, <hi>Ma.</hi> 18.12, 14. <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.24. and to ſave thee, <hi>Ma.</hi> 1.21. and 18.11.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106836:18"/>
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.15, 16. and to take thee where he is, that thou mayſt dwell with him, and be one with him for ever, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.21. Let not therefore his dread, <hi>Job</hi> 13.21. nor thine own trouble and anguiſh, <hi>Job</hi> 15.24, make thee afraid, and think that his faithfulneſs and loving kindneſs ſhall ever fail, <note place="margin">And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thee of the word</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.33. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.10. For, he who is abundant in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and truth, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6. the Lord God of Truth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.5. whoſe words are Truth, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.17. enduring to all Generations, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 100.5. and who is Truth, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.6. will not deny himſelf, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. nor give his glory to another, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.8. and 48.11. for he will bear teſtimony to the word of his Grace, <note place="margin">My hope is as the giving up of the, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 14.3. and albeit thy hopes be well nigh loſt, Ez. 37.11. yet thy faithful Creator, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. who formed thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.1. and 44.2. and 21.24. the God of hope, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.13. who has begotten thee to a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106836:18"/>lively hope, I <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. which hope thou haſt, as an Anchor of the Soul, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.19. will ſuſtain thee with the right hand of his righteouſneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.10. He giveth ſtrength to him that fainteth, and to him that hath no ſtrength he encreaſeth power, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.29. He will not forget thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.15, 19. The needy ſhall not always be forſaken: the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the poor ſhall not periſh for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.18.</p>
               <p>VVill he deſtroy? No: He loveth the works of his own hand, <note place="margin">Wilty thou deſtroy</note> 
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 14.15. Though he cauſe grief, yet will he ſhew compaſſion, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the multitude of his mercies, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.32. He is the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign preſerver of mankind, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights not in the deſtruction of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <hi>Iob</hi> 7.20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.6. and 33.11. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. for mercy pleaſeth him, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.18. and precious in his ſight is the death of his Saints, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.15.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:106836:19"/>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>O but I am at my wits end, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.27. I know not what to do, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 20.12. All refuge fails me, there is none at the right hand to help me, nor at the left hand to care for my Soul, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 142.4. My ſtrength and my hope is periſhed from the Lord, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.14, &amp;c 15. And my Soul refuſes to be comforted, <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.18. <hi>Pſfal.</hi> 77.2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>He that believes makes no haſte, <note place="margin">At my wits end</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.16. Stand ſtill and thou ſhalt ſee the ſalvation of the Lord, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13. who will perfect and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all things for thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.8. And make thee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe able to do all things through his ſtrength, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. Stay thy ſelf upon the Name of the Lord,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106836:19"/>and he will keep thee in perfect peace, <hi>Iſal.</hi> 26.3. Caſt thy burden upon the Lord, he will not ſuffer thee to be moved, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.22. For, <note place="margin">All reſuge fails me.</note> he who is thy reſuge and thy por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the land of the living, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 142.5. well knows how to deliver his own out of troubles, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. Thy help is in the Name of the Lord, who created the Heavens and the Earth, the Sea, and all that therein is; and keeps fidelity for every <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124.8. He is thy help and thy ſhield, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.9, 10, 11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121.2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.10, 13, 14. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">None at the right hand—</note> 44.2. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13.9. His left hand is under thy head, and his right hand doth embrace thee, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.6. Truſt thou always in the Lord, for with the Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> there is everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">My ſtrength and my hope</note> continually, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.5, 14. For the hope of <hi>Iſrael, Ier.</hi> 14.8. And thy hope in the evil day, <hi>Ier.</hi> 17.17. VVho is the ſtrength of thy heart,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106836:20"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.1. and 73.26. VVill fill thee with all joy and peace in believing, that thou mayſt abcund in hope through the power of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.13. Let Chriſt who is the hope of all the ends of the Earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.5. Be in the hope of glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. VVherefore guird up the loyns of thy mind, and hope unto the end, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. And let not the conſolations of God be ſmall with thee, <note place="margin">Refuſeth to be comforted</note> 
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 15.11. For the God of all conſolation, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5. who comforteth all that are caſt down, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.6. who ſent his Son: to (revive, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15.) And bind up the broken hearted, to give unto them that mourn Beauty for Aſhes, the Oyl of Joy for Mourning, the garment of praiſe, for the ſpirit of heavineſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.1, and 3. Bids thee ariſe and ſhine, and put or brightneſs and glory, for the Lord ſhall be a light unto thee in darkneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:106836:20"/>60.2. As one, whom his mother comforteth, ſo will he comfort all that mourn, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.13. VVhy ſhould thy Soul then be diſquieted? for the Father of mercies, and God of all comfort, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3. ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth comfortably unto thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.1. He will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort <hi>Zion</hi> and her Mourners, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.3. and 61.2. The Lord thy God will have thee to ſerve him with joyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and gladneſs of heart, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.47. and always to rejoyce in him, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.16. For there is nothing better, than that a man ſhould rejoyce in his affairs, becauſe that is his portion, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.12.22. &amp;c 5.17. &amp; 2.24.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>He has ſhewen himſelf ſo mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous upon me, <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.9. that aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment has taken me, <hi>Ier.</hi> 8.21. My ſoul is ſore xexed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.8. and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106836:21"/>my heart ſore pained within me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.4, 5. Fearfulneſs and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling are come upon me, and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror hath overwhelmed me, <hi>Ibid.</hi> He has thruſt ſore at me, till I am fallen, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.13. VVo is me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wrath is gone forth againſt me, <hi>Ruth</hi> 1.13. The Almighty has dealt bitterly with me, <hi>Ibidem,</hi> 20. The joy of my heart is ceaſed, <hi>Lam.</hi> 5.15.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>Though his wayes be in the dark, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.9, 11. and 97.2. which for the preſent may ſeem marvelous in thine eyes, <note place="margin">Shewen himſelf marve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.23. yet in the end ſhall they bring forth an excellent and eternal weight of glory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. For he is only wiſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.27. and his love paſleth all knowledge, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.19. If ſorrow therefore has filled thy heart for a ſeaſon, <note place="margin">My Soul, &amp;c.</note> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 16.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106836:21"/>yet let not thy heart be troubled, <note place="margin">My heart ſore pined, &amp;c.</note> neither fear, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.4. and 4.10. and 43.5. <hi>Ier.</hi> 46.27, 28. for thy heart ſhall live for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.26. And rejoyce in the Lord, <hi>Zeeh.</hi> Ie. 7. Go to the Saviour of the World, the Prince of Life, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.15. and 5.31. and he will give thee eaſe to thy ſoul, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. He will rejoyce over thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.5. <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.41. And thou ſhalt rejoyce in his ſalvation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.14. and 13.5. and 20.5. and 35.9. Why is thy ſoul caſt down, and why is it diſquieted within thee? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.5. and 43.5. For he, even he it is that comforts thee, that upholds and confirms thee by the right hand of his righteouſneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.10. Let not thy heart be trouble, <note place="margin">Fearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and trambling.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.27. <hi>Luk</hi> 12.32. Fear not, for thy Redeemer the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is with thee; be not afraid; for he is thy God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.10, 14. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.4. and 44.2, 8. and 43.1, 5.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106836:22"/>
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 30.10. Though his wrath ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hard upon thee. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.7. ſhould preſs thee ſore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.2. and caſt thee down, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.6. yet when thou falleſt, thou ſhalt rife again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.24. and 102.10. And through his wrath thou beeſt now troubled, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.7. And his fierce wrath burning like fire, <note place="margin">VVo is me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wrath is gone, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.46. goeth over thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.16. yet in wrath will he remember mercy, <hi>Hab.</hi> 3.2. and take away all his wrath, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.3. and turn himſelf from the fierceneſs of his anger, <hi>Ibid.</hi> For when Tribulations have abounded, Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhall abound much more, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. He will deal with thee bountifully according to his mercy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.17. and 124. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 142.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.6. And not according to thy corrupt ways and wicked doings, <hi>Ez.</hi> 20.44. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.10. for though he has viſited thy tranſgreſſions with the rod, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106836:22"/>thy iniquities with ſtripes, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs his loving kindneſs will he not utterly take from thee, nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his faithfulneſs to fail, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.32, 33, 34. He will not give thee over unto death, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.18. But aſſuredly ſhew thee greater and mightier things, than thou art able to ſpeak, or think, <hi>Ier.</hi> 33.3. Let his rod comfort thee, <note place="margin">Dealt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly with me.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4. and it ſhall ſhew thee the ſecrets of wiſdom, <hi>Iob</hi> 11.6. And the paths of life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. For the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Lord are right, rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.8. Though thou art in heavineſs for a ſeaſon, through manifold temptations, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.6. yet will he make thee to drink of the rivers of his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; for with him is the fountain of life, and in his light ſhalt thou ſee light, <note place="margin">The joy of my heart is ceaſed.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.8, 9. Then ſhalt thou know the joyful ſound, and walk in the light of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. In his name ſhalt thou walk
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106836:23"/>all the day, and in his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhalt thou be exalted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.15, 16. The righteous ſhall be glad in the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.10. Let them rejoyce before God, yea, let them exceedingly rejoyce. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.3. and draw waters with joy out of the Wells of Conſolation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 12.3. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. from the 10. to the 16. Thou ſhalt obtain everlaſting joy, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.10. and 51.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. and 61.7. which none taketh from thee, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.22. And ſorrow and ſighing ſhall fly away, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.10. Then ſhall thy joy be fulfilled, and remain in thee, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.11. For the kingdom of God doth flouriſh in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and peace, with abundance of joy in the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:106836:23"/>
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>I am preſſed out of meaſure above ſtrength, 2 Cor. 1.8. And ſee no way to eſape, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 20.6. How long wilt thou forget me, O Lord? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.1. How long wilt thou be angry? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79.5. and 85.5. and 80.4. How long ſhall I cry, and thou wilt not hear? <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.2. Why caſteſt thou off my ſoul, and hideſt thy face from me? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.24. <hi>Job</hi> 13.24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.46. and 88.14. Why are thou ſo far from helping me, and from the voice of my roaring? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>O No: Faithful is he who will not ſuffer thee to be tempted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove what thou art able to bear, <note place="margin">Preſted above ſtrength.</note> but with the temptation alſo make a way to eſcape, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. He
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106836:24"/>he will correct in mercy and in Meaſure, <note place="margin">No way to eſcape.</note> 
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 10.24. and 30.11. When he afflicteth thee, he will teach thee the good old way, <hi>Ier.</hi> 6.16. wherein thou ſhouldeſt walk, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.8. For he leadeth the blind by a way that they know not, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.16. He will ſhew thee light, and the way wherein thou ſhouldeſt go, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 32.8. <hi>Neb.</hi> 9.19. and lead thee forth by the right way, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104.7. and make ſtraight in the deſart an high way, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.3. For all the wayes of the Lord are mercy and truth, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 25.10. Can a woman forget her ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Child, <note place="margin">How long wilt thou forget me?</note> that ſhe ſhould not have compaſſion on the ſor of her womb? Yea, ſhe may forget, but he will never forget thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.15. If he cannot forget one ſilly Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, whereof five are ſold for two farthings, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.17. How much leſs will he forget thee created af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his own Image? <hi>Ger.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106836:24"/>and <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24. dignified with the Honourable Title of a Son, <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.36. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. and 9.26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26.1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.16. and 64.8. and Heir, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. <note place="margin">Why caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou off?</note> Will he caſt off his precious Ones? <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.4. <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.8. and 72.14. Whom he has bought, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. and 7.23.2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. with that infinite price of his Sons bloud, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28.1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 19. <hi>Revel.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. VVill he abandon thoſe of whom the world is not worthy? <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.38. Nay, he will earneſtly remember thee ſtill, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.20. Thou ſhalt forget thy miſery, and remember it, as waters that are paſt: <hi>Job</hi> 11.16. <hi>Pro.</hi> 31.7. but he will never forget his tender mercies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.6. nor hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from thy ſupplications, <note place="margin">And hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thy face.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.1. And thou ſhalt behold his face in righteouſneſs, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 17. <hi>last verſe.</hi> He ſhall make his face to ſhine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106836:25"/>thee, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 31.16. and 119.135. and 80.19. Thou ſhalt ſee his face, and his name ſhall be upon thy forehead, <note place="margin">How long wilt thou be angry?</note> 
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.4. Then will he no more cauſe his anger to fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.5. for he is merciful, 12. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6. 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 30.9. <hi>Neb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 9.17, 31. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 103.8. and <hi>Pſa.</hi> 117.2. And will not reſerve his anger for ever, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 30.5. His anger endureth but a moment, he will turn himſelf from the fierceneſs of his anger, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 78.38. <hi>Joſ</hi> 7.26. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 85.3. and cauſe it towards thee to ceaſe, 4. For he retaineth not his anger for ever, <note place="margin">And wilt not hear?</note> 
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.18, 19. If thou lockeſt unto the Lord, and canſt wait for the God of thy ſalvation, thy God will hear thy voice, <hi>Mich. ibid. Numb.</hi> 20.16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.4. and 107.6, 13. and 120.1. and 4.3. and 20.6. 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 7.14. and 20.9. He will anſwer thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.3. and 18.6. and 22.5, 24. for he hears the cry of the afflicted,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106836:25"/>
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.44. <hi>Job</hi> 34.28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 99.6, 8. and it comes near before him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.18. and 88.2. and 102.1. He is nigh to all that call upon him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.18. and 34.18. And his ſalvation a preſent help in trouble, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.9. and 46.1. When the poor and the needy ſeek water and there is none, their tongue faileth for thirſt, the Lord will hear them, the Good of <hi>Iſrael</hi> will not forſake them, <note place="margin">Why caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou off, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.17. He will never fail thee, he will never, never leave thee, nor forſake thee, <hi>Dent.</hi> 4.31. <hi>Joſ</hi> 1.5. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 27.10. and 94.14. and 89.30, 32, 33, 34. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. He has choſen thee, and will not caſt thee away, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.9. <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.26. The Lord will help thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.10, 13, 14. The Lord thy ſtrength will make haſte to help thee, <note place="margin">From helping.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.19. and 38.22. and 40.13. and 70.5. And that right early, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.5. He wil regard the prayer of the deſtitute,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106836:26"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.17. He has not deſpiſed nor abhorred the afflictions of the afflicted, neither has he hid his face from him, but when he cried, he heard him, <note place="margin">The voice of my roaring.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.24. Yea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou calleſt, he will anſwer, &amp; while thou art yet ſpeaking, he will hear, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.5. and receive thy prayer; he wil hear thy ſupplication, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.9. And the voice of thy weeping, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 6.8.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>I am miniſhed and brought low by oppreſſion, affliction, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.10, 39. My confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is always before me, and the ſhame of my face doth cover me continually, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.15. The Lord has rejected my Confidences, that I have not proſpered in them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.37. My heart faints, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.10. and 143.7. My faith fails, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.12.38.10.69.3.119.82. and 123.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106836:26"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.7. My ſpirit is overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med within me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 61.2. and 77.3. and 142.3. and 143.4. My bowels, my bowels, I cannot hold my peace, I am pained at my very heart, my heart maketh a noiſe within me, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.19. becauſe the ſword of the Lord has reached un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſoul, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 4.10, 18. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.35.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>Though thou be ſmall and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <note place="margin">I am brought low.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſ</hi> 119.141. Yet his gentleneſs will make thee great, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 32, 36. He will glorifie thee, and thou ſhalt not be ſmall, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.19. He will remember thee in thy low eſtate, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.23. His lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſs will make thee to encreaſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.35. and bring help to thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.10, 13, 14. and 50.7. and 44.28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.6. The Lord killeth and maketh alive;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106836:27"/>He bringeth down to the grave, and bringeth up; the Lord maketh poor, and maketh rich; he bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth low, and bringeth up, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.6, 7. <note place="margin">By oppreſſion, &amp;c.</note> oppreſſed have no Comforter, <hi>Eccleſt.</hi> 4.1. yet the Lord is their refuge, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.9. and will execute Judgement for them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.7. <hi>Jer.</hi> 21.12. Yea, the Lord executeth Righteouſneſs and Judgement to all that are opreſſed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.6. He will deliver the ſpoiled out of the hand of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor, <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.3. He ſhall break their rods in pieces, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.4. and make thee to rule over them, <note place="margin">By affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.2. He will undo all that afflict thee, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.19. and make thee glad, according to the time wherein he hath afflicted thee, and the years wherein thou haſt ſeen ſorrow, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.15. O thou afflicted, toſſed with tempeſts, and not comforted! <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.11. In righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſS ſhalt thou be eſtabliſhed;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106836:27"/>Thou ſhalt be far from oppreſſion, for thou ſhalt not fear; and from grief, for it ſhall not come near thee, <note place="margin">By ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</note> 14. He has heard and ſeen thine affliction, <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.11. and 29.32. and 31.42. <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.34. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.24. and 106.44. and 25.18. And he, who in all thy afflictions is afflicted, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9. will turn thy mourning unto joy, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.20. He will comfort thee, and cauſe thee to rejoyce from thy ſorrow, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.11. and 61.3. Thy ſoul ſhall be as a watered gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.11. And thou ſhalt ſorrow no more at all, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 31.12. Fear not, <note place="margin">My con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</note> for thou ſhalt not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, for thou ſhalt not be put to ſhame, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.4. Thou ſhalt not be confounded nor aſhamd world without end, <note place="margin">My ſhame.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.17. Believe and thou ſhalt not be confounded, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.7. For thy ſhame thou ſhalt have double, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106836:28"/>for thy confuſion thou ſhalt rejoyce in thy portion, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.7. Yea, thou ſhalt be confounded, and never open thy mouth any more, when he is pacified towards thee, for all that thou haſt done, <note place="margin">The Lord has reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.63. Caſt not away therefore thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.35. But hold it ſtedfaſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6, 14. For he who is the Confidence of all the ends of the earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67.5. ſhall be thy confidence, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.26. The needy ſhall not always be forgotten; the expectation of the poor ſhall not periſh for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.18. God will look on thee, that thou periſh not, <hi>Jon.</hi> 1.6. The Lord thy God will not let thee be aſhamed of thy hope, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.116. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.20. Bleſſed is the man that truſteth in him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.8. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16, 20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.4. Whoſo putteth his truſt in the Lord ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.25. and 28.25. For the ſatisfieth the longing ſoul, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.9. And ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filleth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106836:28"/>the deſire of thoſe that fear him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.19. and 20.5. He will not ſuffer any that wait on him to be aſhamed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.3, and 20. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.23. Believe in the Lord thy God, ſo ſhalt thou be eſtabliſhed, 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 5.20. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 20.20. and 16.7, 8. The Lord will ſend his angel with thee, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.7. and proſper thy way, 56. The Lord ſhall be with thee, and that which thou doeſt, make it to proſper, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.3.23. Delight thy ſelf in the Lord, <note place="margin">My heart faints, &amp;c.</note> and he will give thee the deſires of thy heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.4. Reſt in hope, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.9. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.26. And againſt hope believe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.18. and rejoyce in hope, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2. and thou ſhalt not be aſhamed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5. Wait upon the Lord, and thou ſhalt renew thy ſtrength, and mount up with Wings, as an Eagle, and not faint, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.31. For he giveth power to the faint, and to them
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106836:29"/>that have no might he encreaſeth ſtrength, <note place="margin">My faith fails.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.29. Let nothing have dominion over thy faith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. For he that is the Spirit of Truth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.17. and 15.26. and 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.6. has given thee the Holy Spirit of Promiſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. The World of Truth, <hi>John</hi> 17.17. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. The Word of Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8. and the Spirit of Faith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. He that dwells in the heart by Faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. The Author and finiſher of thy Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. He lives for ever to intercede for thee, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. and prayes for thy Faith not fail thee, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.32. and that thou maiſt have the end of thy Faith. even Eternal Life, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.22. and <hi>John.</hi> 17.24. And till then has not only promiſed never to depart from thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13 5. <hi>John</hi> 14.18. but likewiſe bound himſelf by an everlaſting Covenant to write his fear on thy heart, that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106836:29"/>thou ſhalt never be able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35, 36.</p>
               <p>The God of the Spirits of all fleſh. <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.22. by his viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall preſerve thy Spirit, <note place="margin">My ſpirit is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed.</note> 
                  <hi>Job</hi> 10.12. He will put his Spirit in thee, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.14. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 42.1. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. When thy ſpirit is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welmed, pour out thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint unto the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 142.3. who is thy refuge, and thy portion in the Land of the Living, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. and he will aſſuredly deal bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with thee, <note place="margin">My bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. For his bowels and inward parts do ſound for thee, like and Harp, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 16.11. The ſounding of his bowels and mercies towards thee ſhall not be reſtrained, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.15. his bowels are troubled for thee, he will fure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have mercy upon thee, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.20. And therefore refrain thy voice from weeping, <note place="margin">I cannot hold my peace.</note> and thine eyes from tears, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.16. For in quietneſs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106836:30"/>and confidence ſhal be thy ſtrength, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.15. He looketh upon thy affliction and thy pain, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 25.18. And for thy hurt he is ſo ſore hurt, that aſtoinſhment has taken hold on him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.21. He that wounds and heals, <hi>Job</hi> 5.18. will heal thee of thy wounds, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47.3. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.18. and 10.34.. <note>The ſword of the Lord.</note> He will command his own ſword to be quiet, and put up its ſelf into the ſcabbard, <hi>Jer.</hi> 47.6. neither ſhall any weapon that is formed againſt thee proſper, <hi>Iſa:</hi> 54.17.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>He has made my habitation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.6, 19. <hi>Job</hi> 15.13. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.11. And given my Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance to reproach, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.17. They have called me an Outcaſt, <hi>Jer:</hi> 30.17. I am a deriſion to all my people, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.14. and an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106836:30"/>to my friends, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.8. For they have ſpoken againſt me with lying tongues, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.3. and devouring words, 52.2, 4. which they belch out with their mouths, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.7. The arrows of the mighty man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.4. who has whet his tongue as a ſword, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.3. and 57.4. do ſtick faſt in me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.2. and are ſharp in the heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.5. They have ſet me as a mark for their arrows, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.12. wherewith they have pierced me through, <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.8. They have helped forwards my affliction, <hi>Zach.</hi> 1.15. Reproach has broken my heart, and I am full of heavineſs: I looked for ſome to take pity, and there was none, and for Comforters, but I found none, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.20. Ah my Lord, if thou be with me, why then are all theſe evils come upon me! <hi>Ju.</hi> 6.13.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:106836:31"/>
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>The Lord hath eſtabliſht an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant with thee and thy poſterity, <note place="margin">Made my habitation deſolate.</note> 
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 9. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.39. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.38, 39, 40. He will bleſs the fruit of thy womb, <hi>Det.</hi> 7.13. <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.7. Thy Childrens Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to many Generations ſhall be bleſſed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.25, 26. <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.21. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.2. The Lord Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemeth the ſouls of his ſervants, and none of them that truſt in him ſhall be deſolate, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.22. He will delight in them, to do them good, and to plant them again, with his whole heart and his whole ſoul, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.37. &amp;c 41.44. He will be merciful unto thy dwelling place, that out of it may proceed thankſgiving, and the voice of them that make merry, <hi>Ier.</hi> 30.18, 19. No evil ſhall befall thee, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall any plague come near
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106836:31"/>Thy Tabernacle, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.10, 20. Thy children ſhall be, as aforetime, <note place="margin">My inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance to Reproach.</note> 
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 30.20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128.3. and 90.16. And their Congregation ſhall be eſtabliſhed before the Lord, <hi>Ier.</hi> 30.20. who will puniſh all that oppreſs them,<hi>ibid.</hi> He will pour his Spirit on thy ſeed, and his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on thy offspring, and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Lord ſhall appear unto thy children, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.16. He will no more make thee a reproach amongſt the people, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.19. Thou ſhalt be as a Tree planted by the Rivers of Water, whoſe leaves fade not, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.3. After he has cauſed thee to bear thy ſhame, and all thy tranſgreſſions, then will he be jealous for his holy Name ſake; then will he bring again thy capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and no more hide his face from thee, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.25, 26, 29. Thou ſhalt no more be termed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, <note place="margin">An Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.4. He will reſtore health unto thee, and heal thee of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106836:32"/>thy wound, becauſe they call thee an outcaſt, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.17. Thou ſhalt not be utterly forſaken, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.4. <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9, 10. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.3. And whereas thou haſt been ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſly reported, <note place="margin">An abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on—</note> 
                  <hi>Pſalm</hi> 31.13. <hi>Romans</hi> 3.8. yet the Lord knows thy reproach, and thy ſhame, and thy diſhonour, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 69.10. A wholſome tongue indeed is as a Tree of Life, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.4. And the anwſwer of the Tongue is from the anſwer of the Tongue is from the Lord, <note>place=marg Spoken againſt me—</note> 
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.1. But though a lying tongue hateth thoſe that are afflicted by it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.28. Yet the Lord will recompence tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them that have troubled thee, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.6. Yea, the Lord will deliver thy ſoul, and hide thee from the ſcourge of a deceitful tongue, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120.2. <hi>Job</hi> 5.21. A froward and lying tongue that ſpeaketh proud thing (deviſing miſchief, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52.2. &amp; 50.9.) ſhall be cut off, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Prov.</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:106836:32"/>10.20. for a lying tongue is but for a moment, <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.19. if they have ſpent their Arrows upon thee, made drunk with thy blood, <note place="margin">Arrows of the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty—</note> 
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.23, 42. The gentle and tender-hearted Samaritan will comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate thee, and pouring in Oyl and Wine, bind up thy wounds <hi>Luke</hi> 10.33. Though they have poſſibly ſtript thee of thy Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wounded thee fore, and departed, <note place="margin">Pierced me.</note> leaving thee halſ dead, <hi>verſ.</hi> 30. Yea, though Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould forſake thee, yet the Lord will gather thee up, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.10. He will cover thee with the robes of his righteouſneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.10. And bring forth thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.10. Cauſing the light of thy Cloud to ſhine, <hi>Job</hi> 37.15. The integrity of the upright ſhall preſerve them, <note place="margin">Reproach has bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken my heart.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.21. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.3. It ſhall be clearer, than the Noon-day; thou ſhalt ſhine forth as the Morning, <hi>Job.</hi> 11.17.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106836:33"/>and lift up thy face without ſpot, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. An then ſhalt thou know that better is the poor that walketh in his integrity, that he that is perverſe in his lips, and a fool, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.1. All thoſe that were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed againſt thee ſhall be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and confounded, they ſhall be as nothing; and they that ſtrive againſt thee ſhall periſh, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.11. But thou ſhalt be honoured in the day of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. Thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhall be great in Heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.12. In the mean time he will hide thee from the ſtrife of tongues, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.20. <hi>Job.</hi> 5.21. Surely men of low degree are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <note place="margin">I looked for ſome—</note> and men of high degree are a lye: they are altogether lighter than vanity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.9. and 39.5, 6. But happy is he that hath the God of <hi>Jacob</hi> for his help, whoſe hope is in the Lord his God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.5. Wait thou only upon God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.5. Truſt in him at all times, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106836:33"/>and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.4. for in God is thy ſalvation, and thy glory, the rock of thy ſtrength, and thy refuge is in God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.7. And now that he hath filled thee with bitterneſs, and made thee drunk with Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.15. Confider this in thine heart, <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. and <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.1. Thy way and thy doings have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured all theſe things unto thee, <note place="margin">Ah my Lord!</note> 
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.18. and 50.1. Fools, becauſe of their tranſgreſſions and iniquities are afflicted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 117.17. Yet ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no man knows either love or hatred by all that is before him, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.1, 2. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.14. Do not thou deſpiſe the chaſtiſements of the Almighty; for bleſſed are they whom he chaſtneth, <hi>Job</hi> 5.17. Pſal. 94.12. ſ<hi>Prov.</hi> 13.24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6, 7. And if thou wert without chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then ſhouldſt thou be a Baſtard and no Son, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.8. By partaking of the afflictions of the Goſpel, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.8. And ſuffering
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106836:34"/>with Chriſt, thou ſhalt alſo be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. Who though he many times takes ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on his Children for their inventions, yet will they find him a favourable God unto them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 99.6, 8. making every thing won together for their Good in the end, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. If happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thou knoweſt not now what thy Lord and Maſter is doing to thee, yet thou ſhalt know it afterward, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.7. The man of wiſdom ſhall ſee the name of the Lord, <hi>Mich.</hi> 6.9. who has given thee fair warning, that in the world thou ſhouldeſt have tribulation (An evident token of his love) <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.24. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.6, 7. And of thy ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.28. And that thou art in the right way to the Kingdom of heaven, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.22.) But in him thou ſhouldſt have peace, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.33. And that as a woman after the pain of her labour, forgets he ſorrow,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106836:34"/>
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 10.16.21. ſo ſhalt thou likewiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and thy joy ſhall no man take from thee, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.22. Thy heart ſhall rejoyce in his ſalvation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.5. The Lord will have pity for his holy name, <hi>Ez.</hi> 36.31. <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.18. He will pity thee, as the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pitieth his ſon, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.13. And all theſe evils are but come upon thee, that he may do thee the more good in the later end, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.16. And that where ſin and ſufferings did abound in thee, grace and joy might abound much more, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>Thou haſt brought me to dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and not into light, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.2. I ſit in darkneſs, and in the ſhadow of death, being bound in affliction and iron, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.10. Watch-man, Watch-man, what of the night? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 21.11.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:106836:35"/>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>When thou ſit'ſt in darkneſs without light, <note place="margin">Into dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and not into light.</note> ſtay thy ſelf upon the name of the Lord, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.10. And he ſhall be a light unto thee, <hi>Micah</hi> 7.8. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.6. and 60.19. Light is ſown to the righteous, and joy to the upright of heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.11. He that has delivered thee from the power of darkneſs, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. will make thy light to break forth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.8. and to riſe in obſcurity, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. The Lord ſhall be thy everlaſting light, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.19. He that creates darkneſs, and forms the light, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.7. will make darkneſs light before thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.16. He will light thy candle, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.28. and not quench it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.3.2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.17. The Lord thy God will enlighten thy dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.28. and it ſhall break forth, as the light of the morning,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106836:35"/>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.8. The Lord is thy light and thy ſalvation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.1. He will lift up the light of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance upon thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6. In his light ſhalt thou ſee light, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 36.9. Fear not, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.4. Thy Lamp ſhall not be put out in obſcure darkneſs, <hi>Pro.</hi> 13.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.1. Stay a little, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.16. and 50.10. An Chriſt ſhall give thee light, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18, 23. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.5, 11. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.79. <note place="margin">VVatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, VVatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, &amp;c.</note> The Watch-man ſaith, the morning cometh, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 21.12. Weeping may endure for a night, but joy cometh in the morning, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.5. For the eye-lids of the morning, <hi>Job.</hi> 41.18. ſhall make thy ſeed to flouriſh, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.28. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.14. He that turns the ſhadow of death into the morning, <hi>Amos</hi> 5.8. ſhall cauſe thee to hear his loving kindneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.8. and 92.2. He will bring thee out of darkneſs, and the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.14. In the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106836:36"/>morning thou ſhalt ſee the glory of the Lord, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.17.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>To him that is afflicted pity ſhould be ſhown of his friend, <hi>Job.</hi> 6.14. But though mine eyes have powred out tears unto God, <hi>Job.</hi> 16.20. yet he laughs at my calamity, and mocks when diſtresſs and anguiſh cometh upon me, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.20, 27. And he is cruel to me as the Oſtrich in the Wilderneſs, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.3.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>The Lord is very pitiful, and of tender mercies, <note place="margin">To him that is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted —</note> 
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.11. Though he cauſe grief, yet will he have compaſſion, according to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his mercies, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.32. Thy everlaſting friend <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.3. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23, 31. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.10.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106836:36"/>who changeth not, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Iant.</hi> 1.17. is afflicted in all thy afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in his love and pity has he redeemed thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9. The God of all pity is full of compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.5, 15. and 78.38. and 111.4. and 112.4. and 148.5. <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.8. <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.6. <hi>Num.</hi> 14.18. <hi>Nebem.</hi> 9.17. In him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions (which never fail, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.42.) do plentifully flow, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.38. and 111.4 and 145.8. and 112.4. He will have compaſſion upon thee, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.32. and wipe away all tears from thine eyes <note place="margin">Poured out tears</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.17. He has put thy tears into his bottle, and in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.8. They that ſow in tears ſhall reap in joy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.5. And now behold how he loves thee, for he himſelf, weeps over thee, <hi>Iob.</hi> 11.35, 36. <hi>Lam.</hi> 19.41. Neither is the Lord cruel, <note place="margin">He is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el unto me</note> but meek, <hi>Math.</hi> 11.29. and 21, 5. ſlow to anger, <hi>Neb.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.8.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106836:37"/>And of great kindneſs, <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.13. <hi>Ion.</hi> 4.2. ſince he ſpoke againſt thee, he doth earneſtly remember thee ſtill, he will ſurely have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon thee, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.20. As the Hen gathereth her Chickens under her wings <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37. ſo will he cover thee with his feathers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.4.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>But alas, I fear he has not ſet his love upon me, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.7. He has alienated his mind, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23.18. And taken away his peace, even his loving kindneſs and mereies, <hi>Ier.</hi> 16.5. Wherefore came I forth out of the womb to ſee labour and ſorrow? That my days ſhould be conſumed with ſhame, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 20.18. <hi>Job</hi> 3.11.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:106836:37"/>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>The faithful God Who keepeth Covenant and mercy <note place="margin">He has not ſet his love, </note> 
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.9. has ſaid that he will love thee free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.4. That he will love thee with an everlaſting love, <hi>Fer.</hi> 31.3. 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.16. Greater love could no man have, than this love, that made him lay down his liſe for his friends, <hi>John</hi> 15.13. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in has he commended his love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee, in that when thou waſt yet a ſinner, he died for thee, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. God ſo loved thee, that he gave thee his only begotten Son, through whom thou mighteſt be ſaved, <hi>John</hi> 3.16, 17. No man knoweth either love or hatred by all that is before him, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.1. But in this was the love of God manifeſt to thee, that he ſent his only begotten into the world, that thou mighteſt live through him;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106836:38"/>and that he might be a propitiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for thy ſins, I <hi>John</hi> 3.9, 10. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by mayſt thou well perceive the love of God (who is the God of love, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1. and all love, I <hi>John</hi> 4.8, 16.) That he laid down his life, and gave himſelt for thee, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. Wherein thou mayſt behold what manner of love the Father has beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, that thou ſhouldſt be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led one of the ſons God, I <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.1. He is thy Father doubtleſs, he is thy Father, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.16. and ſo chaſtiſeth thee, not becauſe he is cruel, but even as a Father doth the Son in whom he delights, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.5, 6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.19. He that cannot lye <hi>Num.</hi> 23.19. has ſaid, That he will be thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.8. <hi>Ma.</hi> 6.9. Be ſtrong in the Lord therefore, and in the power of his might, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.10. And be thou perſwaded, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:106836:38"/>ſhall be able to ſeparate thee from the love of the God which is in Chriſt Jeſus, <note place="margin">Alienated his mind.</note> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38, 39. In him there is no varriation, nor ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of change, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Jam,</hi> 1.17. And therefore his loving kindneſs ſhall never depart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.32, 33, &amp;c. <hi>Iſa</hi> 54.10, 11. The FAther him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf loves thee, <hi>John</hi> 16.27. whoſe good pleaſure it is to give thee the Kingdom, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32. &amp; 22.19. Seeing therefore his gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are without repentance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29. He will not take away his feace from thee, <note place="margin">Take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his peace.</note> but enlarge it as a River, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.12. He will reveal to thee abundance of peace, <hi>Fer.</hi> 33.6. And none ſhall take thy joy from thee, <hi>John</hi> 16.22. and 15.11. For his ſure mercies, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3. are everlaſting <hi>Pfal.</hi> 138.8. And his loving kindneſs ſhall never fail, <note place="margin">Even his loving kind ueſss</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.33. He is of thy fleſh and bones, <hi>Fohn</hi> 1.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.3.2. <hi>COR.</hi> 4.11. And no man ever yet hated,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106836:39"/>but rather cheriſhed his own fleſh, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.29, 30. So that well mayſt thou be perſwaded of the Eternal Love of God in Chrifſt Jeſus, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38, 39. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.3. And bleſſed art thou of the Father, who for thee prepared an everlaſting king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34. Who created thee, <note place="margin">VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore came I out of the womb?</note> and took thee out of the womb, <hi>Job</hi> 10.18. <hi>Pſal</hi> 22.9. that thou mighteſt ſee thae goodneſs of the Lord in the Land of the Living, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.13. That being guided by his Council, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.29. Through the many Tribulations, <hi>Fohn</hi> 16.13. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.22. of an evil world, <hi>Gal.</hi> 14.22. of an evil world, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.4. thou mighteſt have Grace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.7. to ſee his manifold wiſdom, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.11. and afterward be received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to glory, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.24. and 84.11. For he created thee, that thou mighſt glorifie him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.1, 2, 21. and be glorified o him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:106836:39"/>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.24. and enjoy him for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.24, to the end. That he might ſo make known the richneſs of his glory on thee a verſſel of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, whom he had before prepared unto glory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.23.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>Haſt thou indeed utterly rejected, haſt thou made thy ſoul to loath me? <hi>Ier.</hi> 14.19. Are thy mercies quite gone for ever? Wilt thou be favourable no more? Has the word of Promiſe failed for ever more? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.7, 8, 9. Did not my Lord and Saviour, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.14, 21. and 49.26. &amp; 60.16. &amp; 63.8. <hi>Ier.</hi> 14: 8. <hi>Hoſ</hi> 13.4. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.47. and 2.11. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.42. I <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.14. (who profeſſed that he was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in all my troubles, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.4. and bade me alſo believe in him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.1. and I <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.23. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.3.) Did he not tell me that he
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106836:40"/>would pray the Father, and he would ſend the Comforter to abide with me for ever, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.16. But alas, where is the promiſe of his coming? I <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter that ſhould relieve my ſoul is far from me, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.16. The Harveſt is paſt, and the Summer is gone, and I am not ſaved, 10.8.20. I looked for peace, and there is no good; and for the time of healing, and behold trouble, <hi>Ier.</hi> 14.19. My ſoul fainteth for his ſalvation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.81. And will he be altogether to me as lyar, and as the waters that fail, <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.18.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>No, no: the Lord will not caſt off his people, <note place="margin">Haſt thou utterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected?</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.14. The purpoſe of God according to Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſhall ſtand, Rom. 9.11. He will not abhor thee for his Name ſake; He will not diſgrace the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106836:40"/>Throne of his glory; He will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, and not break his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Ier.</hi> 14.21. The Covenant of his peace ſhall not be removed, <hi>Iſa:</hi> 54.9, 10. <hi>Ier.</hi> 33.20, 21, 22. and 31.33, 34, &amp;c. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.26! For he is God, the faithful God, that keepeth Covenant and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.4. His ſoul delighteth in thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.1. and 62.4. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.8. yea, he will rejoyce over thee, to do thee good, with his whole ſoul, and his whole heart aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.41.</p>
               <p>The Lord is good, his mercy is everlaſting, <note place="margin">Are thy mercies quite gone?</note> and his truth endureth to all Generations, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 100.5. &amp; 103.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.17. and 54.8. He will not fail thee, <hi>Deut</hi> 31.8. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.1. <hi>Chr.</hi> 18.20. But aſſuredly remember his holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.42. I <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.25. Wait thou therefore upon the Lord, and be of good courage, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. <hi>last. Iſa.</hi> 25.9. For the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106836:41"/>Father has put the Times in his own power, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.7. And will not leave thee comfortleſs; he will come unto thee, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.18. The Prince of peace, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. has left his peace with thee, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.27. deſpiſe not therefore the conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Almighty, <hi>Iob</hi> 15.11. For he will reſtore health unto thee, he will heal thee of thy wounds, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.17. His ſalvation is gone forth, and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs shall not be aboliſhed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.6. and 54.10. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 31.35, 36. He will bring thee health and cure, he will cure thee, and reveal unto thee the abundance of peace and truth, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 33.6. Behold, the day is come, <note place="margin">Has the word of promiſe ſailed?</note> that he will perform the good things that he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.14, 20. For he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfieth the longing ſoul, and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the hungry ſoul with goodneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.17. The needy ſhall not alwayes be forgotten,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106836:41"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.18. <note place="margin">I looked for peace.</note> He that has made an everlaſting Covenant of peace with thee, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.36. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.6. and 54.10. and is become thy God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.1. Is the God of Truth, <hi>John</hi> 14.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.6. I <hi>John</hi> 5.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.7, 14. and 6.10. and no lyar, <hi>Num.</hi> 23.19. His faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs reacheth to the Clouds, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 36.5. He will be juſtified in all his ſayings, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.4. Faithful is he that has promiſed, <note place="margin">VVill he be unto me as a lyar?</note> 
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23. and I <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.24. He is full of grace and truth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14. In him are all the promiſes, Yea, and Amen, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. and 17. He will aſſuredly perform his mercy and his truth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.6. And what he has ſaid, that will he do; what he has ſpoken, that will he make good, <hi>Num.</hi> 23.19.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:106836:42"/>
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>The ſorrows of my heart are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, for I am deſolate, and fore afflicted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.16, 17. The Lord has wounded me with the wounds of an enemy, and chaſtiſed me with the chaſtiſements of a cruel one, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.14. He has taken from me my ſtrenth, the joy of my glory, the delight: of mine eyes, and that whereupon I ſet my mind, <hi>Ez.</hi> 24.25. Verily verily, he has cauſed me to paſs under the Rod, <hi>Ez.</hi> 20.37: I have found trouble and ſorrow, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.3. For I am poor and needy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.1. and 70.5. And my heart is ſore pained within me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.4. <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.4.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:106836:42"/>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>The Lord will not forſake for ever, <note place="margin">The ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of my heart.</note> but though he cauſe grief, yet will he have compaſſion accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the multitude of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.31, 32. Sorrow is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than laughter, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.3. Yet the Lord ſhall even give thee reſt from thy ſorrow, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.3. <hi>Ma.</hi> 11.29. which ſhall be turned unto joy, <hi>John</hi> 16.20. And thou ſhalt have no more ſorrow, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.4. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.12. He who beholds thy deſolations, <note place="margin">I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate.</note> 
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.18. <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.7. and 4.31. will deliver thy deſolate ſoul, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.20. and 25.16. and 35.17. He will give thee a reviving, and repair thy deſolations, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.9. Count it therefore exceeding joy, when thou falleſt into divers tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.2. For whom the Lord loveth he chaſt'neth, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.4. And as thou art partaker of theſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:106836:43"/>ſufferings, ſo ſhalt thou be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the conſolations, <note place="margin">Sore af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted.</note> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4, 7. By afflications art thou magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, <hi>Job</hi> 17.17. that the trial of thy precious faith may be manifeſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. and Patience may have her perfect work, <hi>James</hi> 1.4. and be found unto praiſe, and honour, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 17. and to thy rejoycing with joy unſpeakable, and full of glory, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 18. Like as he has watched over thee to pluck thee up, and caſt thee down to afflict and deſtroy thee, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.28. and has brought all this evil upon thee, ſo will he bring upon thee all the good that he has promiſed thee, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.42. And thou ſhalt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy reproach any more, <hi>Iſa,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Chaſtiſed me.</note> 54.4. If thou be ſmitten of God and afflicted, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.4. it was good for thee (and alſo needful, I <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.) that thou haſt been ſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.71. He that delivereth the poor in all their afflictions, <hi>Job</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:106836:43"/>36.15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.1. regardeth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.17. and is ſore troubled at thine, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9. He will have mercy upon thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.1. and 49.13. and 54.8. and 55.7. And hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py art thou whom he corrects, <hi>Job</hi> 15.17. For whom the Lord loveth he correcteth, as a Father doth the Son in whom he delights, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.19. And though thou be now in heavineſs for a ſeaſon, through manifold tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, I <hi>Pet,</hi> 1.6. yet the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion Rods wherewith thou haſt been chaſtiſed, I <hi>King</hi> 12.11. and 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 10.11, 14. ſhall bloſſom as the Roſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.1. ſhall bloſſom abundantly, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. For as the Earth bringeth forth her Buds, and as the Garden cauſeth the things that are ſown in it to ſpring forth, ſo the Lord will cauſe thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and thy praiſe to ſpring forth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.11. Doeſt thou well then to be angry, that God has
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:106836:44"/>prepared a Worm to ſmite thy Gourd, <note place="margin">Taken from me my ſtrength, &amp;c.</note> whereof thou wert ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding glad, <hi>Jonah</hi> 4.6, 7, 8. When he had pity on thee, to deliver thee out of the belly of Hell, <hi>Jonah</hi> 2.2, 10: And the Lord thy God brought up thy life from corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Jonah</hi> 2.6. Thy true joy ſhall no man take from thee, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.21. A mans life conſiſteth not in the abundance of things which he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.15. The Lord knoweth the thoughts of men, that they are all vanity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.20. Let him therefore that glorieth, glory in the Lord, <hi>Ier.</hi> 9.24. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.31. In whom all things are ours, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.23. And think that bleſſed is he alone whoſe God is the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.8. and whoſe hopes is in the Lord his God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.5. who truſteth in the Lord, in whom there is everlaſting ſtrength, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.4. For ſurely good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and mercy ſhall follow him all
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106836:44"/>the dayes of his life, and he ſhall dwell in the houſe of God for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.6. In the mean time with his Rod will he feed thee, <hi>Mic. 7.14.</hi> and comfort thee, <note place="margin">Paſs under the Rod—</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4. Many indeed are the Tribulations of the Righteous, but the Lord deivereth them out of them all, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.6, 17, 18. <hi>Iob</hi> 5.19. Though thou walkeſt in the midſt of troubles, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.7. yet he who is thy ſtrength in time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.39. and a very preſent help, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.1. is with thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.15. to give thee help, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.11, 12. to deliver thee, <note place="margin">I found trouble.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.1.1 and 54.7. and 91.15. and bring thy ſoul out of trouble, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.11. Thy ſorrows ſhall fly away, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.10. and 51.11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.4. Thou ſhalt ſorrow no more at all, <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.12. Thy heart ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce; yea, it ſhall rejoyce in the Lord, <hi>Zech.</hi> 10.7. and thou ſhalt remember thy miſeries no more,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106836:45"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.7. And though thou be now poor, <note place="margin">I am poor and nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</note> &amp; ſorrowful, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 69.23. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 86.1. &amp; 109.22. Though the encreaſe of thy houſe be departed, and all thy goods be fled away in the day of Gods angew with thee, <hi>Job.</hi> 20.28. yet the Lord is able to give thee much more, than all theſe things, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 25.9. He ſetteth the poor on high from affliction, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.41. He delivereth the needy when he cryeth, the poor alſo, and him that hath no helper, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.12. <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.13. Seeing then he has freely given thee all things, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. and has promiſed to make all things work together for thy good, <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. how can poverty ſeparate thee from the love of God in Chriſt Jeſus? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35. And therefore, although the Fig-true ſhould not bloſſom, neither ſhould fruit be in the Vine, the labour of the Olive ſhould fail, and the Field ſhould yeeld no meat, the flecks ſhould be
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106836:45"/>cut off from the fold, and there ſhould be no herd in the ſtalls, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce thou notwithſtanding in the Lord, and joy in the God of thy ſalvation, <hi>Habak.</hi> 17.18. Nothing ſhall be wanting, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.9. All good things ſhall be miniſtred, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. and God ſhall ſupply all thy needs, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.8, 9, 10. and 84.11.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>He had broken me with his Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind, in the midſt of the Sea, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 27.26. I ſink into deep waters, where the floods overflow me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.2. The ſea is come upon me, I am covered with the multitude of the waves thereof, <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.42. The waters compaſſed me about unto the Soul,<hi>Jer.</hi> 2.5. all thy ſurges, and all thy waves paſſed over me, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.7. and 88.7. I cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in my affliction unto the Lord,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106836:46"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.6. &amp; 30.2, 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.145, 156. and 130.1. Out of the belly of Hell cryed I, <hi>Jonah</hi> 2.2. What profit is there in my blood, when I go down to the pit? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.9. But my Rock and my Lord was ſilent unto me, and anſwered me not, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28.1.2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.42. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.41. He careth not that I periſh, <hi>Mark</hi> 4.38.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>Be of good cheer. <hi>John</hi> 14.1. and encourage thyſelf, <note place="margin">He has broken me—</note> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.6. O thou of little faith! <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.26. and 14.31. and 16.8. He will not break the bruiſed Reed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.3. nor a leaf driven to and fro, <hi>Iob.</hi> 13.25. Believe God that it ſhall be, even as it was told thee, <hi>Act.</hi> 27.25. When thou paſſeſt through the waters, he will be with thee, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 43.2. The water-floods ſhall not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106836:46"/>thee, <note place="margin">Sink in deep wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters—</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.6. The deep ſhall not ſwallow thee up, he will not let the horrible pit ſhut her mouth upon thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.15. Though innumerable evils do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs thee about, <note place="margin">The wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed me.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.12. As the multitude of many waters, <hi>Jonah</hi> 2.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.7. and 88.7. yet he that truſteth in the Lord, mercy ſhall compaſs him about alſo, <note place="margin">All thy waves.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.10. He will rebuke the winds and the waves, and ſpeak unto the ſea, <hi>Mark</hi> 4.39. For he is the confidence of all thoſe that are afar off upon the ſea, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.5. And when thou cryeſt unto the Lord, <note place="margin">I cryed in my affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</note> he will reſtore thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.2. He will bring thy ſoul out of the grave, and will revive thee from them that go down into the pit, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. The Lord thy God will bring up thy life from the pit, <hi>Jonah</hi> 2.6. The Sea ſhall render up her dead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.13. The hearer of prayers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.2. will regard,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106836:47"/>and not deſpiſe the prayers of the afflicted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.17. He will hear thy voice; for ſalvation is of the Lord, <hi>Ionah</hi> 2.2, 6, 7, 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17. and 17.6. <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.7. and 145.19. Thy heavenly Father, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.14. and 26.42. The Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign preſerver of men, <hi>Iob.</hi> 7.20. who delights not in the deſtructions of ſinners, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.11. will hear the groaning of the priſoner, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.20. and 10.7. and 17.6. His ears are open to thy cry, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.15. When thou cryeſt he will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.15. and 99.6. and 50.15. <hi>Ier.</hi> 19.12. He that cannot forget thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.50. and 49.15. careth for thee, <note place="margin">He careth not—</note> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7. He remembreth thee carneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtill, therefore his bowels are moved for thee; he will ſurely have mercy upon thee, <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.20. He that has ſo loved thee, as to give his dear Son (who did alſo pour out even his foul unto the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:106836:47"/>death for thee, <note place="margin">That I preiſh.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.10, 12.) that thou mighteſt not periſh, will he now abandon the works of his own hands? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31, Which he has bought with a price of ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite a value, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. and 7.23. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. If he reconciled thee to God his Father, while thou wert yet an enemy, how much more being now joyned to him by affinity, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. and 63.16. <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.30. and conſanguinity, <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Can.</hi> 4.9. and 5.1. Will he care for thy ſoul? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. Now that ſhe is ſo precious in his ſight, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.4. pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, beautified with his Graces, <hi>Can.</hi> 7.1, 2, &amp;c. covered with the Robes of his Righteouſneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. and one with himſelf, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.21. And that thou mayeſt know what manner of love he carrieth to thee, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.1, 2. He has given thee
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106836:48"/>the earneſt of the Spirit of Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a pledge, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15, 16. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.5.2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. The Oyl of joy for Mourning, the garments of Gladneſs for Heavineſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.3. And the firſt fruits of Life Eternal, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. Yea, if the Son of God dwell in thee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. And the holy Ghoſt make a Temple of thy body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. and 6.19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. How canſt thou but be beloved, precious and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in his ſight? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.15. If a good man regardeth the life of his beaſt, <hi>Pro.</hi> 12.10. How much more will he, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth man and beaſt? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.6. that feeds the fowls of the air, and cloaths the grafs of the field, <hi>Mat:</hi> 6.25, 26, 30. who cannot forget the ſilly Sparrows, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.4. and has numbred the hairs of thy had, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. deliver thine eyes from tears, and thy ſoul from death?
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:106836:48"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.8. ſeeing he has made thee a little lower than the Angels, crowned thee with honour and glory, and made thee to have do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over the works of his hands, putting all things under thy feet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.5, 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>O he is holy, and I am but a worm, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.14. <hi>Job</hi> 25.6. Though I have made him my everlaſting Joy, my Glory, and my God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.19. yet has he filled me with bitterneſs, and made me drunk with Wormwood, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.15. He has made me the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring and refuſe in the midſt of the people, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.45. and broken me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.8. and 44.19. <hi>Ez.</hi> 27.26. with a tempeſt, <hi>Iob</hi> 9.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.6 and 83.15. Of his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion poured out upon me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.49. <hi>Ez.</hi> 22.31: <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.8. He bade
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:106836:49"/>me come unto him, that I might have peace and reſt to my ſoul, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. and that I may get life, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.40. yet when I enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged my heart to approach unto him, <hi>Ier.</hi> 30.21. and poured out my complaint before him, like the waters, <hi>Iob</hi> 3.24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 142.2. And looked up unto my Father, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.22. <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.7. till mine eys failed, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.32. <hi>Iob.</hi> 11.20. making my ſupplication to my Judge, <hi>Iob</hi> 9.15. He not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding covereth himſelf with a cloud, that my prayers ſhould not paſs through, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.44. He puts away his Servant in anger, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.9. and caſts me out from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.11. to the loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my perſon, <hi>Ez.</hi> 16.5. <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.8. <hi>Pro.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.6. O did ever man thus hate his own fleſh! <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.29. And ſhall his faithfulneſs even fail in my deſtruction? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.11.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:106836:49"/>
               <head>The <hi>Comforter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And wilt thou indeed thus foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly charge, <note place="margin">I have made him my ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting joy, &amp;c. But he made me the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring.</note> 
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.22. the Lord God of Truth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.5. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.6. and make one of ſo glorious, ſo precious, ſo near, and ſo dear relations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.1, 21. and 44.21. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.16. a lyar, <hi>Num.</hi> 23.19. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.4. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10. Wilt thou belie the Lord? <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.12. thy Creator? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.1. and 48.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.11. thy Father, <hi>Mat. 6.9. Rom.</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32. <hi>Eph.</hi> 12. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.2 <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. thy Redeemer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.5. and 71.23. and 74.2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.14. and 43.14. and 44.22. and 49.26. and 60.16. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. thy elder Brother, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. The Husband, and Bridegroom of thy ſoul, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.8, 9, 10, 11, 12, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.5 and 62.5. and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:106836:50"/>not ſtay the ſelf upon his Nature and his Name, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.20. and 50.10. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 30.19. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.17. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 86.15. and 111.4. <hi>John</hi> 2.13. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 145.8. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 16.21. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 54.6. and 79.9. and 138.2. <hi>Jer.</hi> 11.5. Nor be comforted by the great Oath of the everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.13, 14, 17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.23. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.2, 4, 7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3. and 61.8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.60, 62. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.26, 27. Has he not ſaid, though he be high, yet will he have reſpect to the lowly, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.6. The high and lofty One, who inhabiteth E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, whoſe name is holy, though he dwell in the high and holy place, he dwells alſo with him, who is of a broken and humble ſpirit, to revive the ſpirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite ones, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. He has always heard the deſires of the humble, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17. And he will
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:106836:50"/>regard the prayers of the deſtitute, <note place="margin">He cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with a cloud</note> and not deſpiſe their prayers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.17. Verily God will hear, he will attend to the voice of thy prayer,, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18, 19. In the day when thou cryeſt, he will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thee, and ſtrengthen thee with ſtrength in thy ſoul, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.3. Wait therefore patiently upon the Lord, and he will incline unto thee, and hear thy cry, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.1. He never yet prepared any heart to pray, but the cauſed alſo his ear to hear, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17. Whoſoever cometh unto him, theſe will he no ways caſt out, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. though for the preſent, thou be drunk in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but not with Wine, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.9. and 51.21. And through many a ſad ſtroke, <hi>Iob.</hi> 23.2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.6. ſtaggering like a drunken man, <note place="margin">He has made me drunken with worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 107.27. yet mayſt thou repair when thou wilt to the Wells of Salvation, and draw waters of joy with gladneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 12.3. Yea, thou
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:106836:51"/>ſhalt one day drink of the rivers, of theſe pleaſures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.3. which are at his right hand, and laſts for evermore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Of the pure River of the water of Life, clear as Cryſtal proceeding out of the Throne of God, and of the Lamb, <hi>Iob.</hi> 4.10, 14. <hi>Revei.</hi> 22.1. His fruit ſhall be ſweet unto thy taſte, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.3. His words and his ways ſhall be ſweet to thy ſoul, as the honey comb, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.17. and 16.24. <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.63, 68. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.10. Though thou art become vile, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.11. and men now ride over thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.12. yet art thou honourable in Gods account, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.4. He who exalteth the low Tree, making it to flouriſh, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17.24. and lifteth the needy out of the dung-hill, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.7, 8.1 <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſal.</hi> 113.7. and 147.6. will cauſe thee to ſhine forth, and thou ſhalt be as the morning, <hi>Iob.</hi> 11.17. He will bring forth thy r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ghteouſneſs
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106836:51"/>as the light, and thy Judgments is the noon-day, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.6. Though thou haſt been amongſt the pots, yet ſhalt thou—as the wings of a Dove covered with Silver, and their feathers with yellow Gold, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 68.13. For God will bleſs the name of the righteous, with favour will he compaſs them, as with a ſhield, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.12. and honour them that honour him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. He has but affrayed thee with his ſtorm, <note place="margin">Broken me with a tempeſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 93.15. but he will make the ſtorm a calme, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.29. He is a covert, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.6. and refuge from the ſtorm, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.4. His indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and his anger ſhall ceaſe. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 10.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.3, 4. and 103.9. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.5, 12. <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.18. For he has not ſaid to the houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> Seek ye my face in vain? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.19. Nay, <note place="margin">That my prayers cannot paſs tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</note> he is found of them that ſeek him not, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.20. And while thou art yet a far way off, he ſhall meet thee, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.20. yea, while thou
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:106836:52"/>art ſpeaking and preſenting thy ſupplication before the Lord thy God, he will anſwer thee, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.20, 21. Verily he will hear thee, he will not turn away thy prayer, nor his tender mercies from thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.20. He will receive thy prayer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.8. and attend to the voice of thy ſupplication, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.22. He will be very gracious to thee at the voice of thy cry, when he ſhall hear it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.19. For the eyes of the Lord are upon the righteous, and his ears are open unto their cry, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.15. The righteous cry, and the Lord hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, and deliveteth them out of all their troubles, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.17. and 107.6, 13, 19, 28. and 50.15. Shall the Hen gather her Chickens under her wings? <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.34. and the Sea-Monſter draw forth her breaſts to her young ones? <hi>Lament.</hi> 4.3. And will thy Emmanuel, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.23.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106836:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>hide himſelf from his own fleſh? <note place="margin">Did ever man thus hate his own fleſh?</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.7. and 65.4. will he hide his face from thee? <hi>Ez.</hi> 39.29. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.17. Nay, he will rather cauſe his face to ſhine, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.16. and 67.1. and 80.1, 3. And lift up the light of his countenance upon thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6. and 43.3. and 44.3. He will hide thee under the ſhadow of his wings, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.8. and in the ſecret of his preſence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.20. For the Lord deſpiſeth neither thy perſon, <note place="margin">From his preſence, to the loathing of my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.33. and 40.17. and 70.5. nor thy prayers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.17. His precious Jewels, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. will he hide in the ſecret of his Tabernacle, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.5. and his tender Lambs will he carry in his boſome, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.11. And though thou ſhouldſt not believe, yet abideth he faithful, and will not deny himſelf, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23. <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.138. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.24. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.3. In the Eternal thy righteouſneſs,
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:106836:53"/>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 23.6. to whom righteouſneſs belongeth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.7. ſhalt thou have righteouſneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.24. He is the faithful God which keepeth covenant, <note place="margin">Shall his faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs—</note> 
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. His faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs reacheth unto the clouds, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.5. And he will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to fail, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.33. unto all generations, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.19. Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and juſt is he to forgive they ſins, and cleanſe thee from all thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, 1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.9. The Lord is faithful which ſhall ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh thee, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.3. and will not take his loving kindneſs from thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.33.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>The Lord has puniſhed me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my ways, <hi>Hoſ</hi> 4.9. and 22.2. And recompenſed me accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fruit of my doings, <hi>Jer.</hi> 21.14. He has filled me with
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:106836:53"/>the fruit of my own way, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.31. till I am even waſted away, <hi>Job.</hi> 14.10, 20. The Lord has ſent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me vexation and rebuke, in all that I ſet my hand unto for to do, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.20. He has ſmitten me with blindneſs, and aſtoniſhment of mind, 28. He has made my plague wonderful, even great plagues, and of long continuance, <hi>verſ.</hi> 59. He has given me a trembling heart, failing of eyes, and ſorrow of mind, <hi>verſ.</hi> 65. He has vexed me in his ſore diſpleaſure with all adverſity, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 15.6. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Job</hi> 27.2. And as he once rejoyced over me to do me good, ſo doth he now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce over me to deſtroy, and bring me to nought, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.63. See, O Lord, and conſider, for I am become vile, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.11.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:106836:54"/>
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>Why ſhouldeſt thou, <note place="margin">The Lord has pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed me.</note> a living man, complain for the puniſhment of thy ſin? <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.31. and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther think it exceeding joy when thou falleſt into divers temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.2. Believing that thou art bleſſed, becauſe chaſt'ned, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 94.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6.7. If he has chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thee ſore, yet has he not given thee over to death, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.18. chaſt'ned thou art indeed of the Lord, that thou mayeſt not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned with the world, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.32. And if thou be without cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement, then art thou a Baſtard, and not a Son, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.8. Thy God has puniſhed thee, and exacted leſs than thy iniquities deſerve, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 9.13. <hi>Job.</hi> 11.6. If thou accepteſt of the puniſhment of thy iniquities, then will he remember his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.41, 42. The Lord
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106836:54"/>will have mercy upon thee after thou haſt born thy ſhame, <hi>Ez.</hi> 39.25, 26. And will not hide his face any more from thee, <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. The man of ſorrows, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.3. Upon whom was laid the chaſtiſements of thy peace will wipe away the tears, and take away the rebuke, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.8. of thoſe, for whom he was ſtricken, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.8. <note place="margin">Sent upon me vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion—</note> He will heal and deliver thy ſoul from vexation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.2. and 55.18. and keep thee in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect peace, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.3. He who is thy peace, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.14. has ſent to thee alſo the Goſpel of peace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15, 16. <hi>Eph:</hi> 6.15. The Lord of peace himſelf, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.33. has given to thee the peace of God to rule in thy heart, <hi>John</hi> 14.27. and 16.33. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.2. and 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.11. and 85.8. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.12. and 66.12. <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.13. and 33.6. He that opened the eyes of the blind, <note place="margin">Smitten me with blindneſs.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.30. <hi>Mark</hi> 8.22, &amp;c. <hi>Jo.</hi> 9.1, 2, 3, &amp;c. will
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:106836:55"/>enlighten thy darkneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.28. and deliver thee from the power thereof, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. that in his light thou mayſt ſee light, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.9. and walk through darkneſs, <hi>Job</hi> 29.3. and that the eyes of thy underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing being enlightned, thou mayeſt then be aſtoniſhed at the richneſs of the glory of his Inheritance in the Saints, <note place="margin">With a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> 
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.18. If he has ſhewed himſelf marvelous upon thee, <note place="margin">My plague wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</note> 
                  <hi>Job</hi> 10.16. by great plagues and ſore afflictions, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 71.20. and 118.18. and 119.107. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.32. by enlarged troubles, and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied vexations, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.17. and 34.19 and 42.7 and 88.7 by conſuming ſtroaks, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.10. and 37.19. and 90.7. and continued ſorrow and grief, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.1, 2. and 77.8, 9. yet will he remember the word of Truth which he has given, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.49. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.16. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.60. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.25. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.— and make every thing work
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:106836:55"/>together for thy good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. He will not forget, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.15. and 54.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.6. the greatneſs of his mercies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.10. and 86.13. and 108.4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.7. and multitude of his compaſſions, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.13. and 51.1. and 78.38. and 86.15. and 111.4. and 145.8. and 112.4. But as thy ſufferings abound, ſo ſhall thy conſolations abound alſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.5. And though he ſhould bring thee to nought, <note place="margin">Bring me to nought.</note> yet he that creates new Heavens, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.17. he that forms the light, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.7. will cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate thee a rejoycing, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.18. The God of thy ſalvation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.5. and 68.19, 20. and 79.9. and 85.4. to whom belong the iſſues from death, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.20. will create a defence upon all thy glory, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.5. And for thy momentany and light afflictions, thou ſhalt have a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. He ſhall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie thy longing ſoul, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.9.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106836:56"/>and 145.16. and 103.5. with ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of everlaſting joy, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.7. <hi>John</hi> 17.13.—For in his preſence is fulneſs of joy, at his right hand there are pleaſures for evermore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. Be of good courage therefore, and wait upon the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.14. and 31.24. For he has ſeen, he has ſeen thy afflictions, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.7. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.24. which have not made thee vile, <note place="margin">I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vile.</note> 
                  <hi>Job</hi> 7.17. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.20. Yea, thou art precious and honourable in his ſight, who loveth thee, created thee for his glory, and formed thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.3, 4, 7. who thought not the world worthy of thee, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.38. and ſpared not his own Son, but gave him to die for thee, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. and has made thee Son and Heir of God through Chriſt, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.7.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:106836:56"/>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>My dayes are conſumed in vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and my years in trouble. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.33. My life is ſpent with grief, and my years with ſighing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.10. Innumerable evils have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed me about, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 40.12. and my ſorrow is continually before me, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 38.17. and 44.15. O my God, my ſoul is caſt down within me! <hi>Pſa.</hi> 42.6. It is poured out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, <hi>Job</hi> 30.16. Becauſe thou haſt caſt off, and put to ſhame, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 44.9. Thou haſt hid thy face from me, and conſumed me, becauſe of mine iniquities, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 64.7.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>Yet the Lord is with thee in trouble, <note place="margin">My days are conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in vanity—</note> 
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 91.15: thy refuge in the day of affliction, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 9.9. and 57.1. and 59.16. and 62.7, 8. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 25.4.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:106836:57"/>and 4.6. <hi>Jer.</hi> 16.19. and thy hope the evil day, <hi>Jermiah</hi> 17.17. Surely mercy and goodneſs ſhall follow thee all the days of thy life, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 23.6. In the time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble he will hide thee in his Pavilion, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 27.5. He will make thee glad, according to the days wherein he has afflicted thee, and the years wherein thou haſt ſeen evil, <note place="margin">And my years in ſighting.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 90.15. The ſighings of the Priſoners ſhall come before him, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 79.11. For the ſighing of the needy will he ariſe, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 12.5. Though thou faint in thy ſighing, and can find no reſt, <hi>Jer.</hi> 45.3. yet there remaineth a reſt for the people of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9. The Lord ſhall give thee reſt from thy ſorrow, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.3. Thou ſhalt find reſt for thy ſoul, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Ma.</hi> 11.28, 29. He will recompenſe reſt to thee for thy troubles, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.6, 7. <note place="margin">Innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable evils have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed me.</note> Wherefore ſhouldſt thou fear in the days of evil, when the iniquities of thy heels do compaſs thee about
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:106836:57"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.5. For he will chaſe them away as a cloud, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.22. and remove them from thee, as far as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.12. Fear not; for if thine eyes were opened — thou ſhouldſt ſee more with thee, than againſt thee, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.16, 17. The Angel of the Lord encampeth about them that foar him, and delivereth them: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.7. He will help and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. and 37.4. The Lord is with thee, to ſave thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.1 and 35.4, <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.20. and 30.11 and 46.27. Thou ſhalt be ſaved in the Lord, with an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſalvation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.17. He will ſave thee unto the uttermoſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. Thy ſighing ſhall fly away, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34.10. <note place="margin">My ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</note> And thy ſorrow ſhall be turned unto joy, <hi>John</hi> 16.20. for be that repleniſheth every ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſoul, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.25. will fill thee with joy, <hi>John</hi> 17.13. and thou ſhalt ſorrow no more at all, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.12
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:106836:58"/>O thou of little faith! <note place="margin">My ſoul is caſt down.</note> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.26. &amp; 14.31. &amp; 16.8. and of a fearful heart, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.4. Why is thy ſoul caſt down? why is it diſquieted within thee? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.5, 11. &amp; 43.11. He will exalt thee in due time, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.6. The Lord bringeth low, and lifteth up, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 113.7. &amp; 147.6. He will deliver thy ſoul from the hand of the grave, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.48. &amp; 49.15. The Lord will not caſt off for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.7. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.37. He will not caſt off his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 94.14. <hi>Lem.</hi> 3.31. The Lord thy God ſhall hear thee, and thou ſhalt be, as if he had not caſt thee off, <hi>Zech.</hi> 10.6. Thou ſhalt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be aſhamed, <note place="margin">Put to ſhame.</note> 
                  <hi>Joel</hi> 2.26, 27. Thou ſhalt not be aſhamed in the evil time, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.19. Whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.33. and waiteth on him, ſhall not be aſhmed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.33. and 54.4. Thou ſhalt not be put to ſhame, <hi>ibid.</hi> The Lord knows thy reproach &amp; thy ſhame, <hi>Pſt</hi> 69.19
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:106836:58"/>And for thy ſhame thou ſhalt have double, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.7. He that made an everylaſting Covenant with thee, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.35, 36. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.26. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3 &amp; 61.8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.60. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20. Thy everlaſting Light, thy God, and thy Glory, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.20. will not hide his face from thee, <note place="margin">Hide thy face.</note> 
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.29. He that ſent his only begotten Son out of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome unto the world, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Gal:</hi> 4.4, 5.1 <hi>John</hi> 4.9, 10.1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. The Sovereign Preſerver of men, <hi>Job.</hi> 7.20. and the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> thy Saviour, <note place="margin">Conſumed becauſe of mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.8. <hi>John</hi> 4.14. 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.14. who redeems thy life from deſtruction, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.4. will not deſtroy thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.17. for thoſe ſins which he had blotted out, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.25. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14. and taken away, <hi>John</hi> 1.2, 36. Thy ſins are forgiven thee for his Names ſake, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.12.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:106836:59"/>
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>If I ſay I will forget my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, I will leave off my heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and comfort my ſelf; then am I afraid of all my ſorrows, <hi>Iob.</hi> 9.27, 28. When I would comfort my ſelf againſt ſorrow, my heart is faint within me, <hi>Ier.</hi> 8.18. For through ſorrow of heart my ſpirit is broken, <hi>Pro.</hi> 15.13.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>Encourage thyſelf in the Lord, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.6. whoſe delights are with the Sons of Men, <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.31. In the multitude of thy thoughts, <note place="margin">A fraid of all my ſorrows.</note> let his comforts delight thy ſoul, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 94.19. For he delighteth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.4. and will have his joy fulfilled in thee, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.12. that thou mayeſt always rejoyce, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.1. and 4.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.1. and 97.12.—<hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.16.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:106836:59"/>The Lord comforts all that mourn, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.2 and 66.13. and 49.13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.12. and 66.13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4. and 7.6. Hold faſt thy confidence, and the rejoycing of thy hope firm unto the end, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6. Do not quit the Crown of thy rejoycing in the hour of temptation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.11. If the arrows of the Almighty be within thee, and the poyſon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of drink up thy ſpirit, <hi>Iob.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 45.5. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.19. There is Balme in <hi>Gilead,</hi> and a Phyſician there, <hi>Ier.</hi> 8.22. The tender-hearted Samaritan will pour in Oyl and Wine into thy wounds, and have compaſſion upon thee, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.33, 34. The great Comforter, <hi>John</hi> 14.16. who in all tribulations, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. comforteth thoſe that are caſt down, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.6. And revives the heart of the contrite ones, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. will anoint thee with the Oyl of gladneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.7. and cheriſh thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.12. with the ſweet
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:106836:60"/>Wine of his Conſolations, <hi>Amos</hi> 9.13. <hi>Can.</hi> 2.5. He that was ſent to bind up the broken-hearted, and to comfort all that mourn, <note place="margin">When I would comfort my ſelf—</note> 
                  <hi>Iſ.</hi> 61.1, 2. will not leave thee comfortleſs, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.18. He will reſtore comforts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 57.15. and make thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations to abound, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. in everlaſting joy, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 61.7. The ſpirit of man is the candle of the Lord, <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.27. which he has quickned, <hi>John</hi> 6.63. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1. and lighted, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 18.28. And ſeeing he is become thy everlaſting light, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 60.19, 20. <note place="margin">My heart is faint,</note> and thou art made one ſpirit with him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. and <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.21. having received the Spirit of Adoption, <note place="margin">My ſpirit is broken.</note> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Faith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. and art thereby ſtrengthned with might, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.16. Why ſhouldſt thou faint? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16. and ſuffer thy ſpirit to be broken? <hi>Pſa.</hi> 42.5, 11. and 143.7. and not rather be glad in the Lord, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 32.11. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.4.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106836:60"/>and 3.1. and rejoyce with him, who (though he was a man of ſorrows, and acquainted with grief, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 53.35. yet) rejoyced in ſpirit, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould have revealed the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Counſel of his Good Will to be the matter of thy continual joy, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.20, 21.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>What ſhall I ſay then after this? <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1. He who did bear my iniquities, and carried my ſorrows; he who was wounded for my tranſgreſſion, and broken for my iniquities, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.4. Is he not able to juſtifie me? <hi>verſe</hi> 11. Shall not his ſoul which he poured out unto death, <hi>verſe</hi> 12. be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient offering for my ſin? <hi>verſe</hi> 10. Is not he that did tread the Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs of the fierceneſs and wrath of the Almighty God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.15. the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,<hi>v.</hi>16
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:106836:61"/>able to ſave me? <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.12. O will not he, that ſo loved me, that he gave himſelf to death for me? <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.13. Deliver me from all my tranſgreſſions? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.8. and from the wrath to come? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. ſeeing the Father has given him power over all fleſh, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>Yes verily,<note place="margin">He who did bear my iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp;c. Is he not able?—</note> he is able and willing alſo to ſave thee to the utmoſt, <hi>Heb:</hi> 5.7. and 7.25. and 7.18. <hi>John</hi> 17.24. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.20. for he juſtifies the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5, 25. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33. and 5.16, 18. and giveth Eternal life unto them, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.28. And this is the will of God, That whoſoever believes in his Sor, ſhould have life everlaſting, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.40. &amp; 20.31. In him ſhalt thou be juſtified and ſhalt glory, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24, 28. and 5.1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.7. Thou waſt bought with a price, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20.—
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:106836:61"/>purchaſed with the precious blood to Chriſt, <note place="margin">A ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent effer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> 
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28.1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. and God has given his own Son to be the propitation for thy ſins, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.2. and 4.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. ſo that thou maiſt now joy in God, being reconciled to him through the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom thou haſt received the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10, 11. and 3.25. The offering of the body of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as an everlaſting ſacrifice has perfected thee for ever, <note place="margin">Is he not able to ſave me?</note> 
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.10, 14. Thy redeemer is mighty, <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.1. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.17. to deliver thee, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. and <hi>Ia.</hi> 1.21. for he is God the Lord, to whom nothing is unpoſſible, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.14. <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.17, 27. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.8. The Lord thy God will deliver thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. He whom God has exalted to be a Saviour, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31. and 13.23. by his grace ſhall ſave thee, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.3, 7, 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.8. <hi>Fph.</hi> 2.5, 8.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:106836:62"/>
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 55.16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Ier.</hi> 30.11. &amp; 15.20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24. He that was anointed to preach the Goſpel to the poor, ſent to heal the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken-hearted, to preach deliverance to the Captive, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. and the opening of the priſon to them that are bound, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.1. He will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver thee, and honour thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. and 91.5 <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. He that was delivered to death for thy offences, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25. is the God of thy Salvation, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 18.46. &amp; 24.5. &amp; 3.8. <hi>Ionah</hi> 2.9. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.4. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. and will deliver thee from the wrath that is to come, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5. Thou ſhalt be ſaved in the Lord with an everlaſting ſalvation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.17. He whoſe name is Jeſus ſhall ſave his people from their ſins, <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.6. The ſon of man did come to ſeek, and to ſave that which is loſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.10. God
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:106836:62"/>ſent his Son into the world, that the world through him might be ſaved, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.17. For a faithful ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is, and worthy of all accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, That Chriſt Jeſus came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world to ſave ſinners, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. in whom thou haſt redemption through his blood, even the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of ſins, according to the richneſs of his Grace, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. And the Glory which the Father gave him, has he vouchſafed on thee, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.22. Nor can he have any reſt, till thou be, where he is, that thou mayeſt partake of the fulneſs thereof, <hi>verſ.</hi> 24.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>O when ſhall Mortality put on Immortality! 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. That I may know the bleſſedneſs of thoſe that die in the Lord, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. And the good of his choſen, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.5. When ſhall I enter into my
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:106836:63"/>Maſters joy, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.21. and my Fathers Kingdom, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.34. Who will bring me unto the City where the Lord is? <hi>Ez.</hi> 48.35. that I may be with him for ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.5. <hi>John</hi> 17.24. And ſee light in his light, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.9. and know the richneſs of his glorious Inheritance in the Saints, <hi>Fph.</hi> 1.19. When ſhall I drink of the Rivers of theſe pleaſures which are at his right hand, and taſte of theſe joys that laſt for ever more? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. When ſhall I know that love of Chriſt that paſſeth all knowledge? <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.19. O when ſhall I praiſe God, and magnifie his name toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.3. with thoſe who were killed for the Word of God, and for the Teſtimony which they maintained! <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9. How long, O Lord, which art holy and true, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.10. wilt thou forget, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.1. the priſoner in the pit! <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.11.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:106836:63"/>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>Yet a little while, and he that came, <note place="margin">When im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty—</note> will come and not tarry <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.37. Behold he comes quickly, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.11. and 22.7. and 12.20. to render unto thee Immortality, and Eternal Life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.7.1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.53, 54.2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. Thou ſhalt ſtand up in thy Lot at the end of thy days, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.13. and then ſhall the Lamb that was killed and redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee unto God by his blood, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. preſent thee holy and unblameable in the preſence of his Fathers glory with exceeding joy, <hi>Jude verſ.</hi> 24. Then ſhalt thou awake unto everlaſting Life, and ſhine as the brightneſs of the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, and as the Stars for ever and ever, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2, 3. and know the exceeding richneſs of his Grace through his kindneſs towards thee in Chriſt Jeſus, <note place="margin">That I ma know the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs—</note> 
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.7. Through
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:106836:64"/>whom thou haſt entrance unto the Father, and ſhall be no more a Stranger, but a Citizen with the Saints, and of the Houſhold of Faith, <note place="margin">Who will bring me into the City?</note> 
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.18, 19. He that has upon his garment, and upon his thigh, a name written (a name which no man knoweth but himſelf, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.12.) The King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. The Prince of the Kings of the Earth that loved thee, and waſhed thee from thy ſins with his own blood, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5, 6. The Almighty, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. who has the key of Hell, and of Death, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. He that is holy and true; he that hath the key of <hi>David,</hi> and openeth, and no man ſhutteth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7. ſhall bring thee to the Holy City, the New <hi>Jeruſalem, Revel.</hi> 21.2. As thou haſt heard, ſo ſhalt thou ſee in the City of thy God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.8. The gladneſs of his Nation, and thou ſhalt glory with his inheritance,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:106836:64"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.5. Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his beauty, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. Thou ſhalt behold the Land, though yet afar off, <hi>ibid.</hi> There ſhalt thou be as the Angels of God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.30. Nay, like Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. to whoſe Image thou ſhalt be made conformable, <note place="margin">That I may be with him, and ſee light in his light.</note> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. With him ſhalt thou be, <hi>John</hi> 14.3. and 17.24. 1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 4.17. And ſee his face, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.4. and behold his glory, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.22, 24. and 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.12. He that is the Way, the Truth, and the Life, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.6. The bright Morning Star, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.16. and the Son of Righteouſneſs, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2. ſhall lead thee into the land of uprightneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.10. where thou ſhalt inherit, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take all the Promiſes, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.33. and 6.12, 15. which thou ſhalt then find to be no cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly deviſed Fables, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16. but the day-ſpring of that glorioas Light, and the ſeals of that Harveſt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:106836:65"/>of Joy which is ſown for the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.11. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16.13.2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Acts.</hi> 20.32. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.16. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, 19, &amp;c. The Word of Truth, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.17. <hi>Iames</hi> 1.18. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Pro.</hi> 22.21. in the everlaſting Goſpel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6. The pouring out of the name of God as a precious Oyntment, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.3, <note place="margin">The riches of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance.</note> for in that day he will ſhew thee greater and mightier things, than thou couldeſt have asked or thought of, <hi>Ier.</hi> 33.3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.4. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.20. He hath promiſed thee a Kingdom, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34. An Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Kingdom, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21.2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.18. An Eternal Kingdom, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. A Crown, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.11. A Crown of Life, <hi>Iames</hi> 1.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. A Crown of righteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. An immarceſſible Crown of Glory, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.9. Thus being crowned with glory and honour, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.7, 9.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:106836:65"/>And with his loving kindneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.4. And being fill'd with the fulneſs of God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.19. Thou ſhalt be more able to comprehend the breadth, and length, and depth, and height of the love of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.19. who is the God of love, <hi>2 Cor.</hi> 13.11. and all love, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.8, 16. who ſo loved thee, that he would give himſelf for thee, <note place="margin">VVhen ſhall I drink of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver? —</note> 
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. Then ſhalt thou find how ſweet, and how gracious the Lord is, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.8.1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.3. who will give thee free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to drink of the Waters of life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 12.3. and 45.8. and to eat of the Tree of Life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.2. and of the hidden Manna, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.17. In that day ſhalt thou drink of the pure Rivers of the Waters of Life, clear as Cryſtal, proceeding out of the Throne of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.1. Then ſhall the faithful and true Witneſs, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.5. and 19.11. who chaſt'ned
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:106836:66"/>and rebuked thee in the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he loved thee, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.19. When he has brought thee through many tribulations and given thee a long and white Robe, made white in his blood, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.11. and 7.9, 14. with a Crown of Glory on thy head, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.4. And a Palm of victory in thy hand, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.9. and ſet thee down upon the Throne with himſelf, <note place="margin">When ſhal I know that Love?</note> 
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. let thee know what manner of love he hath beſtowed upon thee, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.1. For thou ſhalt inherit all things; God ſhall be thy God, and thou ſhalt be his Son, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7. And thus being taken up into the New Heavens, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13 the New <hi>Jeruſalem, Rev.</hi> 21.2. <note place="margin">When ſhal I magnifie his Name?</note> He will write upon thy forehead his New Name, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.12. He will alſo put a New Song in thy mouth, which no man can learn but the Redeemed from the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.3. The firſt
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:106836:66"/>fruits unto God, and unto the Lamb, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. And thus exalted in the righteouſneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.16. of him that ſet his heart upon thee to chooſe thee, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.7. before the foundations of the world were laid, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. Thou ſhalt ſing the ſong of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the ſong of the Lamb, ſaying, Great and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous are thy works, Lord God Almighty, juſt and true are thy wayes, thou King of Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.3. Who will not fear thee, and glorifie thy Name? For thou only art holy, and now thy Judgements are made manifeſt, <hi>verſe</hi> 4. Thou ſhalt ſing with thoſe who overcame by the Blood of the Lamb, and by the Word of their Teſtimony, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.11. ſaying, Now is come ſalvation and ſtrength, and the kingdom of our God, and the power of his Chriſt, <hi>verſe</hi> 10. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and Glory and Wiſdom, and Thankſgiving and Honour, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:106836:67"/>power and might, be unto our God for ever and ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.12. and 5.12, 13. We give thanks, O Lord God Almighty, becauſe thou haſt taken unto thee thy great power, and has rainged, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.17. Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God Almighty, which was, and is, and liveth for ever and ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.8, 9. Thou art worthy, O Lord, to receive Honour, and Glory, and Power, for thou haſt created all things, and for thy pleaſure they are and were created, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. Rejoyce therefore in the hope, <note place="margin">How long O Lord?</note> 
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6. of that Glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. whereunto thou art begotten by the in mortal ſeed of the Word, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. which is ſhortly to be revealed, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. and 5.1. for the time is at hand, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.10. wherein thou ſhalt be, as thou art ſeen, and know, as thou art known, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. for, though thine eyes, while thou art in the World, cannot be ſatisfied with
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:106836:67"/>ſeeing, nor thine ears with hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 18. And it cannot enter into thy heart what great and mighty things God has prepared for his beloved ones, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. Yet when thou ſhalt be admitted to ſup, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20. with the Eternal, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.10. <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.33. with the Living God, that everlaſting King, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.28. at the Marriage of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.7, 9. thou ſhalt make an Eternal Feaſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.10. and 51.11. and 61.7. of fat things, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.6. and eat and drink abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly with the Bridegroom and his friends, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.1. Then ſhall thy-joy be full, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.13. Thou ſhalt rejoyce with <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and be glad with her; thou ſhalt ſuck and be ſatisfied with the breaſts of her Conſolation, and be delighted with the brightneſs of her glory, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.10, 11. Thou ſhalt be abundantly ſatisfied with the fat things of his
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:106836:68"/>houſe, and he will make thee to drink of the Rivers of his pleaſures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.8. Then ſhalt thou taſte the bleſſedneſs of that people, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in their God; thou ſhalt walk in the light of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and rejoyce in his name continually, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.15, 16. and with all the Creatures which are in Heaven and in Earth, ſhalt thou give praiſe, and honour, and glory, and power, unto him that ſits upon the Throne, and unto the Lamb for ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.13. and 7.13. He that confirmed the Word, <note place="margin">Wilt thou forget?</note> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth the counſel of his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, even the Lord that formed thee ha not forgoten thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.21, 24, 26. The Lerd has ſent (thy Lord <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1.) to bind up the broken-hearted, and to open the priſon to thoſe that are bound, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.1, 2. and 42.7. Has he not graven thee on the palms of his hands? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.16. and ſet thee as a
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:106836:68"/>Seal on his heart? <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6. Thou art continually before him, how can he forget thee? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.15, 19. Nay, out of his love to thy Soul, be hath delivered it from the pit of corruption, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.3.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="point">
               <head>The Soul.</head>
               <p>I long to ſee that City whereof ſo glorious things are ſpoken, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.15. And the people that have no Sun, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21: 3. no Temple, 16.22. no Winter, 16.23. no. Woe, 16.4. I long to ſee the Antient of Days, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.3. my everlaſting Friend, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.14, 15. and my Father — Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. I long to ſee my El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Brother, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. And to meet with the Spouſe of my Soul, <hi>John</hi> 3.29. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14. and to ſee the thouſands of my brethren ſtanding with the Lamb in mount
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:106836:69"/>
                  <hi>Zion, Rev.</hi> 14.1. I long to hear the voice of Joy and Gladneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.8. the voice of my Beloved, that made my Soul many tirnes to fail, when he ſpoke to me, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.6, 16. and the harping of the Harpers about the Trone, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.2. I long to ſmell theſe Oyntments for which the Virgins love him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.3. I long to taſte of the Tree of Life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.2. and the food of Angels, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.25. <hi>Jo.</hi> 6.31. I long to be embraced, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.6. and 8.3. of the beauty of Holineſs, 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 16.29. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 20.21. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.2. and 99.9. and 110.3. and to enjoy <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.24. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.10. and praiſe him for ever, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="counter-point">
               <head>The Comforter.</head>
               <p>He that hath mercy upon thee will lead thee, <note place="margin">I long to ſee that City—</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.10. by the way everlaſting, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.24. into the land of upringhtnneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.10.
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:106836:69"/>He will bring thee in through the Gates unto that great, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.10. and Holy City, 16.2. And in due ſeaſon, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.9. when thou haſt finiſhed thy courſe, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 7.8. and run the race that is ſet before thee, <hi>Heh.</hi> 12.1. he will ſhew thee the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> preparced as a Bride adorned for her Husband, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.2, 10. That City of pure Gold, like unto clear Glaſs, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. and her great and high Walls, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. whoſe foundations are garniſhed with all manner of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. and her twelve Gates which are twelve Pearls, and the Streets of the City which were of pure Gold, as it were tranſparent Glaſs, <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. wherein there is no Temple for the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb are the Temple of it, <note place="margin">No Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> 
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. and the City has no need of the Sun, <note place="margin">No Sun—</note> neither of the Moon to ſhine in it, for the glery of God
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:106836:70"/>doth light it, and the Lamb is the light thereof, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. and all the Citizens are children of light; <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.8. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.8. 1 <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 5.5. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.23, 24. and 22.4. who have obtained a Crown of life, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.12. and the Joy of their ſalvation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. <hi>Jo.</hi> 16.24. and 17.13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. and all tears being wip't from their eyes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.8. do know no more ſorrow nor crying. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.4. for God himſelf dwelleth with them, they are his people, and he is their God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7.3. who has put everlaſting joy upon their heads, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.10. and 51.11. and 61.7. which is alſo prepared for thee, when thou comeſt to thy Fathers Kingdom, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.24. and to Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> and to that City of the Living God, the Celeſtial <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and to the company of innumerable Angels, and to the Aſſembly and Congregation
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:106836:70"/>The Firſt-born, which are written in Heaven, and to the Spirits of juſt and prefect men, <note place="margin">I long to ſee theAntient of Dayce.</note> 
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.22, 23. If thou longeſt to find out the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, <hi>Job.</hi> 11.7. who is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in Power, and in Judgment, <hi>Job</hi> 37.23. and the moſt High whoſe Kingdom is an everlaſting Kingdom, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27. Thou ſhalt then behold him to thy prefection, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>John</hi> 3.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. He will no more ſhew himſelf through the Lattice, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.9. but the wall being removed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.20. Thou ſhalt ſee his face, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.4. as the Sun in the ſtrength of his Glory, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.2. with thoſe eyes of thine ſhalt thou ſee thy Redeemer, <hi>Job</hi> 19.25, 27. Thy everlaſting joy, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.10. and 51.11. and 61.7. thy glory, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.19. and thy God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.2, and 22.1, 2, 10. and 48.14. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.10. <hi>Mitab</hi> 7.7. whoſe delights were with the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:106836:71"/>Sons of Men before he prepared the Heavens, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.27, 31. Thou ſhalt meet with him in the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetting Houſe, <note place="margin">To meet with the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom.</note> 
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.4. In the ſecret of his Tabernacle, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.1. and 27.5. and nothing ſhall ever be able to ſeparate thee from the Love, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.39. of thy Bridegroom, who has married thee to himſelf in Righteouſneſs and tender Mercies, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.19. Then being admitted to that Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Communion with the Father, and the Son, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3.1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9. and the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1. thou ſhalt ſee and know that Wiſedome which the Lord poſſeſſed in the beginning of his. Way before his Works of Old, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 8.22. Thou ſhalt ſee the Aſſembly of Saint, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.7. <note place="margin">The thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw.</note> 
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.1, 2, 3, &amp;c. joyful in Glory, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.5.— and ſhouting aloud for joy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.9, 16. having the high praiſes
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:106836:71"/>of God in their Mouth, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 149.6. ſaying, Hallelejah, Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and Glory, and Honour, and Power be unto the Lord, <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.1, 6. He that ſatiſfieth the longing ſoul, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 107.9. will perfect and perform what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever concerns thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 138.8. and ſupplying all thy needs according to his glorious Riches in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.19. If thou delighteſt thy ſelf in the Lord; he will give thee all the deſires of thine heart, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 37.4. and being crowned with loving kindneſs, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 103.4. Thou ſhalt reign with him for ever and ever <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.5. <hi>John</hi> 17.24. Then ſhall he be thy portion, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 73.26. Thou ſhalt be One in him, and he in thee, <hi>John</hi> 17.21. Thou ſhalt praiſe and walk in the Name of the Lord thy God for ever and ever, <hi>Micah</hi> 4.5.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:106836:72"/>
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.20. Then ſhall Chriſt be All in All, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.28. And all things ſhall likewiſe be thine, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:106836:72"/>
               <head>The <hi>SOUL</hi> comforted, and confirmed by the Right Hand of the Lords Righteouſueſs, and the Spirit of the Holy <hi>Promiſe,</hi> breaks out in this following Divine Rapture, and Valedictory to the world.</head>
               <p>ONce have I ſpoken, but I will not anſwer; yea, twice, but I will proceed no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Behold, I am vile, what ſhall I anſwer? I will lay my hand upon my mouth, <hi>Job</hi> 40.4, 5. I have hear'd, I have hear'd the ſtill ſoft voice of the Lord, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.12. the voice of him that ſpoke, as never man did; <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.46. which makes the Soul to burn, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.32.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:106836:73"/>
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.6. The voice of my Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.8, 10. whoſe Lips are like Lillies, dropping ſweet-ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Myrrhe. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.13. Enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Rock, and hide the ſelf in the daſt, my Soul, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.10. Cover the face with a Mantle, while the Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> proclaims his Name, and maketh all his goodneſs to paſs before thee, <hi>Exoad.</hi> 33.22. Bow thy ſelf to the ground, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.6. and rejoyce with rembling, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.11. for in his month is the Law of kindneſs, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.26. And he hath publiſhed the glad tidings, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.7. and 66.12. He hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed the abundance of his peace unto thee, <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.6.</p>
               <p>This, this indeed, in the power of God unto Salvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. the light of that glorious Goſpel, which hath ſhined, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. and is come unto me, not in word, but alſo in Power, and in the Holy Ghoſt, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5. This is that
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:106836:73"/>Spirit of Wiſedom, and Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the God of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath given to me in the knowledge of him, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.17. and of the myſtery of his Will, according to his good pleaſure, which he had purpoſed in himſelf, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.9. And this Word of Truth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.17.1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.5, 14. (through the riches of his free Grace, by whom I have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.7.) will I receive, with much aſſurance, and joy of the Holy Ghoſt, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5. for he hath put gladneſs in my Heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.7.</p>
               <p>And now methinks I hear a voice falling from Heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.35. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.13. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.31. A voice of joy and gladneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.8. and 105.43. and 106.5. ſaying, Come unto me, and I will give thee peace, and reſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. and 25.34. I'le ſhow thee, I'le give thee greater, and mightier
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:106836:74"/>things than ever thou wert able to ſpeak or think of, <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.3. Come enter into thy Maſters joy, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Kingdom, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.21. where thou ſhalt inherit all things. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. Methinks I ſee a Door opened in Heaven, and hear a voice, as it were, of a Trumpet, talking with me, and ſaying, Come up hither, <hi>Revel.</hi> 4.1. and I will ſhew thee the path of Life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11: I'le ſhew thee my Salvation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.16. I'le ſhew thee the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing riches of my Grace, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.7. and my marvelous loving kindneſs <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.7. I'le ſhew thee the Bride, and the Lambs Wife, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9.</p>
               <p>O that I had wings like a Dove, that I might fly, and be at reſt! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.6. for I have ſeen an end of all perfection, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.96. like as the Hart panteth for the Water. Brooks, ſo panteth my ſoul for thee: Lord, when ſhall I come
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:106836:74"/>and appear before thee? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.1, 2. I had rather be a Door-keeper in the Houſe of my God, than dwell here, though in Chambers of pleaſure, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.10. Come Lord Jeſus, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17. and haſten the coming of thy Promiſe! 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4, 12. Come quickly, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.7, and 20. for I have waited, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.18. I have hoped, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.166. I have longed for thy Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.174. O Let thy Servant depart in peace! <hi>Luke</hi> 2.29. for I know whom I have believed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 31.3. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. and that thy glory will alſo be great in my falvation! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.5. Now let the Prince of this world, <hi>John</hi> 12.31. and 14.30. and 16.11. ſhew me all the Kingdoms of the Earth, and give me all the power and glory thereof, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.5, 6. I count all things but dung and loſs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3, 4.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:106836:75"/>and that love of his which paſſeth all knowledge, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.19.</p>
               <p>And indeed, who would dwell in houſes of clay? <hi>Job</hi> 4.19. that have eternal Manſions prepared for them in the Heavens, not made with hands? <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.2, 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10. who would chooſe rather to remain ſtill in <hi>Meſech,</hi> and in the Tents of <hi>Kedar, Pſal.</hi> 120.5. than to dwell in the ſecret place of the Moſt High and abide under the ſhadow of his Wings? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.1. In a <hi>Babylon</hi> of Confuſion, the Mother of Harlots, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.5. appointed unto deſtruction, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.10, 22. rather than in that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of my God: The Heavenly, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22. the New, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.12. and the Holy <hi>Jeruſalem, Rev.</hi> 21.2, 10. which is the Mother of the beloved Ones, that are redeemed from the Earth? <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. and 14.3, 4. and to have their converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the men of this world,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:106836:75"/>
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.17. and 18.36.1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.12. and 5.10. With the Children of <hi>Belial,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.17. and 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 13.7. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15. Rather than with the Angels, and Glorified Saints, which are without fault before the Throne of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.5. Now depart from me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.8. All creature comforts, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.14, 17. and 9.9. and 3.18, 19. Too long have you bewitched me, with your Vanities and Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 4.2. Waſting and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction are in your crooked paths, <hi>Iſaia.</hi> 59.7. Whoſoever walketh therein, ſhall find nothing but folly and madneſs, <hi>ibid.</hi> 8. <hi>Ec.</hi> 9.3. and 10.13. Your Vine is of the Vine of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and of the Fields of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah;</hi> Your Grapes are of Call, and of the Poyſon of Dragons; Your Cluſters are bitter, and as the cruel venom of Aſps, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.32, 33. For I did take hold of folly, till I might ſee that goodneſs of the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:106836:76"/>Children of Men, which they enjoy under the Sun, the whole number of the days of their life, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.3. And behold all is Vanity, and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Spirit: There is no profit under the Sun, <hi>ibid.</hi> 11. For all the Days of Man are ſorrow, and his Travel grief, <hi>ibid.</hi> 2.3. But ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted be the God of my Salvation, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.47. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 18.46. In whom I will rejoice, <hi>Hah.</hi> 3.18. For he hath ſpread the Banner of his Love over me, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.4. He hath an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed me with the Oyl of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.7. And fed me with Honey taken out of the carkaſe of the ſtrong Lyon. <hi>Judg.</hi> 14.9. So that though the iniquities of my heels do compaſs me about, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 49.5. And all the world ſhould forſake me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.10. Yet being juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. And kept by the power of God unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. and 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.4. I will not fear, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. and 26.24.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:106836:76"/>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.4. and 41.10, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 27.3. But even glory in my Tribulations, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3. Therefore awake up my Glory, awake Pſaltery and Harp, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 57.8. And meet the Deliverer with Triumoh, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.2. and <hi>Pſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 70.5. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 144.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.26. for his right hand, and his holy Arm hath gotten thee the Victory, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 98.1.2. And becauſe he hath made me an eternal excellency, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60, 15. I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore offer Sacrifices of immortal praiſes in the Temple of Eternity, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.11, 12.</p>
               <p>Come unto me then, O Death, thou King of Terrour, triumphing upon thy pale Horſe, with Hell fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing after thee! <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.8. I now defy thy Impotent, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.54, 55, 56. and Tim. 1.10. I provoke thy welcom Dart, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 55.6, and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7. and 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12. for I am covered with the ſhield of Faith, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.8. And armed with
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:106836:77"/>the Breaſt-plate of Righteouſneſs, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.14. wherewith I am able to quench it, <hi>ibid.</hi> 6.16. I have alſo received the Spirit of Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. and the pardon of my ſins, <hi>Luke</hi> 5.20. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. and 4.32. As the Watch-man watcheth for the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.6. and the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-man waiteth for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Fruit of the Earth, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.7. ſo have I waited for thy coming, <hi>Job</hi> 14.14. ſo do I long to paſs through thy ſilent Valeys, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21, 23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.6. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.29. that I may reap the Harveſt of joy, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.3. and 35.10. and 61.7. <hi>John</hi> 16.24.1 <hi>John</hi> 1.4. and 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. Shall the ſouls under the Altar be ſtill crying with a loud voice, How long, O Lord, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.10. and the whole Creation travel in pain, to be delivered from the bondage of Corruption, into the glorious liberty of the Children of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:106836:77"/>God? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21, 22. And ſhall not I, who have received the Firſt-fruits of the Spirit, even groan within my ſelf, waiting for the Adoption? <hi>ibid.</hi> 23. And for the appearance of Chriſt, who is my life? <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4. for I am ſure that my Redeemer liveth; and though worms deſtroy this body, yet ſhall I ſee God in my fleſh, whom I my ſelf ſhall ſee, and mine eyes ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and none other for me, <hi>Job</hi> 19.25, 26, 27. Then ſhall that word be fulfilled, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.11. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9. Death is ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in Victory, O Death, where is thy ſting? O Grave, where is thy victory? 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 15.55. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.10. And now Holy Father glorifie thy Servant with the ſelfe (according to theſe Teſtimonies of thy Grace, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.3. and 20.32. and all theſe precious words of thy Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:106836:78"/>that thou haſt given him, on which thou haſt cauſed him to hope, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.49.) that his joy may be full, and he may alſo glorifie thee for ever.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:106836:78"/>
            <head>Books Printed and Sold by <hi>Dorman Newman.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>Quarto.</head>
               <item>THat Excellent Piece of Mr. <hi>George Swynnocks</hi> Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Calling, in three volumns, Directing the Chriſtian how to make Religion his Buſineſs in all Relations, Conditions, and Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences that may fall out in his whole life.</item>
               <item>Faiths Univerſal Uſefulneſs, with the Excellency of a Spiritual Life. By that famous man of God, Maſter <hi>Matthew Laurence</hi> of <hi>Ipſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Elborough</hi>'s Sermon on the Fire.</item>
               <item>There is now extant that much expected book of Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Boroughs,</hi> Entituled, <hi>Goſpel Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:</hi> Wherein is diſcovered, Firſt, the many and great Goſpel My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries therein contained. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
<pb facs="tcp:106836:79"/>the glorious effects pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from it. Thirdly, the miſtakes that are made about it. Fourthly, the true Signs and Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes of it. Fifthly, the way and means how to obtain it.</item>
               <item>The Virtue and Value of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme Catechetically propounded as an Antidote gainſt all Baptiſm-deſpiſing Dictates. By Mr. <hi>Zach. Crofton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That much expected Piece of Mr. <hi>Durham,</hi> Minister in <hi>Scotland,</hi> his Expoſition upon the whole Book of <hi>Canticles,</hi> or <hi>Song of so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> is now in the Preſs, and almoſt Printed.</item>
               <item>Doctor <hi>Hamptons</hi> Sermon before King <hi>James.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Leſtey's</hi> Sermon tending to Unity</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hampton's</hi> Three-fold State of man.</item>
               <item>A Sermon before King <hi>James.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hiſtory of the Gentle Craft.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:106836:79"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dod</hi> and <hi>Clever</hi> on the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</item>
               <item>Soules Sentinels.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spicers</hi> Elogie on Sir <hi>Arthur Cheſter.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Octavo.</head>
               <item>THe Life of Cardinal <hi>Woolſey,</hi> that famous Lord Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. With the Remarks upon thoſe Times, not unworthy the peruſal of ours.</item>
               <item>The Excellency of the Pen and Penſil, exemplifying the Uſes of them in the moſt Exquiſite and Myſterious Arts of Drawing, Etching, Engraving, Limbning, Painting in Oyl, waſhing Maps and Picture: Alſo the way to cleanſe any old Painting, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Colour: Furniſhed with divers Copper Cuts.</item>
               <item>A guide to Ladies, Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="tcp:106836:80"/>and Maids, how to behave themſelves in all Eſtates, Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Conditions by <hi>Hannah Wolley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A guide to the True Religion, Directing how to make a wiſe Choice of the Religion men Venture their Salvation upon. By <hi>J.Clapham,</hi> M. A.</item>
               <item>The Chriſtians great Intereſt, or a ſhort Treatiſe divided into two Parts, The firſt whereof contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Trial of a Saving Intereſt in Chriſt. The ſecond pointeth forth plainly the way how to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it; wherein ſomewhat is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſpoken to the manner of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Covenanting with God. By <hi>W. Guthry,</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Scotland.</hi> The Fifth Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</item>
               <item>Juſtification only upon a Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction; or the Neceſſity and Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the Satisfaction of Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:106836:80"/>as the alone ground of Remiſſion of ſin, aſſerted and opened againſt the Socinians. By <hi>Robert Fergir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Paſtors Love to a Loving People. By Mr. <hi>William Thomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Synopſis</hi> of Quakariſme, or a Collection of the Fundamental Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the Quakers.</item>
               <item>With a brief Refutation of their moſt Material Arguments (and particularly <hi>W. Pen's</hi> in his late <hi>Sandy Foundation ſhaken</hi>) and an Eſſay toward the Eſtabliſhment of private Chriſtians in the Truth oppoſed by thoſe Errors. By <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Danſon,</hi> ſometime Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Sandwich</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Laws and Canons drawn up, and agreed upon by the
<pb facs="tcp:106836:81"/>General Aſſembly or Meeting of the Head of the Quakers from all parts of the Kingdom.</item>
               <item>Phanatick Primer for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Little Ones, in order to perfect reading. By <hi>H. Adis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rebukes for ſin by Gods Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Anger, by the burning of the City, the burning of the World, the burning of the Wicked; with a Diſcourſe of Heart-fixedneſs. By <hi>Thomas Doolittle.</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</item>
               <item>The Life of Doctor <hi>James <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> late Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> and Primate of all <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A moſt Comfortable and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Dialogue. By Mr. <hi>William Cooper.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Spare Minutes: or Reſolved Meditations, and premeditated Reſolutions: by <hi>Arthur Warwick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clariſſimi Viri Adriani Heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boordi Philoſophiae profeſſoris Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii
<pb facs="tcp:106836:81"/>Diſputationum de Concurſu Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amen a Johanne Stearne M. D. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutum ad Amicum ſuum Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Rawlineum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Excellent Oration of that late famouſly Learned <hi>John Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds,</hi> D. D. and Lecturer of the Greek Tongue in <hi>Oxford,</hi> very uſeful for all ſuch as affect the Studies of Logick and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, and admire Profane Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Archers</hi> Jeſts.</item>
               <item>Heaths Tranſubſtantiation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sejanus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Owen</hi>'s Epigrams.</item>
               <item>King <hi>James</hi> Meditations.</item>
               <item>None but Chriſt.</item>
               <item>Four Select Sermons upon ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Texts of Scripture, wherein the Idolatry and Will-worſhip of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is laid open and confuted. By Mr. <hi>Will. Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar</hi> of <hi>Rochford,</hi> never before pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:106836:82"/>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Fames Maltons</hi> twenty Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons preached on ſeveral Texts, <hi>viz.</hi> Mans Petition, and Gods Compaſſion ſhewed, on <hi>Pſalm</hi> 138.3.</item>
               <item>Mercy deſpiſed, and God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked thereby, on <hi>Pſalm</hi> 106.24.</item>
               <item>Chriſts Pretionſneſs, on 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7.</item>
               <item>The neceſſity of Humiliation, on <hi>Acts</hi> 16.29, 30.</item>
               <item>Chriſt the Bread of Life, on <hi>John</hi> 6.35.</item>
               <item>Chriſts two Diſciples doers of Gods will, on <hi>John</hi> 7.17.</item>
               <item>Fear of loſing Salvation, and the way to obtain it, on <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.1.</item>
               <item>The Perſevering Saint ſhall be <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.11.</item>
               <item>Walking in Chriſt a ſign of our right receiving of Chriſt, on <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6.</item>
               <item>Light Diſcovered, and Man
<pb facs="tcp:106836:82"/>Recovered, on <hi>1 Tim.</hi> 1.10.</item>
               <item>Chriſts Temptation, the Saints Supportation, on <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2. and the laſt Verſe.</item>
               <item>Chriſts proviſion for man Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, on <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.11.</item>
               <item>Heaven upon Earth, or the Beſt Friend in the Worſt Times. By <hi>James Janeway.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Unhappy Proſperity expreſſed in the Hiſtory of <hi>Aelius Sejanus,</hi> and <hi>philippa</hi> the <hi>Catamian.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Practice of Quietneſs, derecting a Chriſtian how to live quietly in this troubleſome world.</item>
               <item>The CHURCH MILLITANT, Hiſtorically continued form the Year 33. to the Year 1640. By Sir <hi>William Vaughan,</hi> Knight.</item>
               <item>A moſt Comfortable and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian DIALOGUE between the Lord and the Soul. <hi>By Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam
<pb facs="tcp:106836:83"/>Cooper,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loway.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hollingworths</hi> Juſtification. In <hi>Duodecimo.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106836:83" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
